<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The apologie of Pierce Pennilesse. Or, strange newes, of the intercepting certaine letters and a conuoy of verses, as they were going priuilie to victuall the Lowe Countries. By Tho. Nashe gentleman.</title>
            <title>Strange newes, of the intercepting certaine letters, and a convoy of verses, as they were going privilie to victuall the Low Countries</title>
            <author>Nash, Thomas, 1567-1601.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1592</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08013</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18378</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103117</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838874</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838874</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3264</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08013)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3264)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1211:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The apologie of Pierce Pennilesse. Or, strange newes, of the intercepting certaine letters and a conuoy of verses, as they were going priuilie to victuall the Lowe Countries. By Tho. Nashe gentleman.</title>
                  <title>Strange newes, of the intercepting certaine letters, and a convoy of verses, as they were going privilie to victuall the Low Countries</title>
                  <author>Nash, Thomas, 1567-1601.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[88] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Iohn Danter, dwelling in Hosse-Lane neere Holburne Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1593.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Harvey, Gabriel.  Foure letters, and certaine sonnets.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-L⁴ M² .</note>
                  <note>Printer's device (McKerrow 281) on title page.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Foure letters confuted.</note>
                  <note>Another issue of "Strange newes, of the intercepting certaine letters, and a convoy of verses, as they were going privilie to victuall the Low Countries" (STC 18377), with the preliminaries printed on two leaves.</note>
                  <note>First 2 leaves closely cropped at head; M3, final leaf, stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Harvey, Gabriel, 1550?-1631. --  Foure letters, and certaine sonnets --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3264:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3264:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> Apologie of Pierce Pennileſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR</hi> Strange Newes, Of the intercepting certaine Letters, and a Conuoy of Verſes, as they were going <hi>Priuilie</hi> to victuall the Lowe Countries.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndae impellitur vndae.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Tho. Naſhe</hi> Gentleman</p>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>Iohn Danter,</hi> dwelling in Hoff<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Lane neere Holburne Conduit, 1593.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3264:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the moſt copious <gap reason="illegible: page cropped" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> perſecutor of <hi>Priſcian,</hi> his very friend Maiſter <hi>Apis La<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is: Tho. Naſhe</hi> wiſheth new ſtrings to his old tawny Purſe, and all honorable <hi>increaſe of acquaintance in the Cellar.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle M. <hi>William,</hi> that learned writer <hi>Rheniſh Wine and Sugar,</hi> in the firſt booke of his Comment vpon <hi>Red-noſes</hi> hath this ſaying: <hi>veterem ferendo iniuriam inuitas nouam,</hi> which is as much in engliſh, as one Cuppe of nipitaty puls on another. In moyſt conſideration whereof, as alſo in zealous regard of that <hi>high</hi> countenance you ſhew vnto Schollers, I am bold in ſtead of new wine, to carowſe to you a cuppe of newes: which if your worſhip (according to your wonted <hi>Chauceriſme</hi>) ſhall accept in good part, Ile be your daily O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator to pray that, that pure ſanguine complexion of yours may neuer be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſht with pot-lucke, that you may taſt till your laſt gaſpe, and liue to ſee the confuſion of both your ſpeciall enemies, Small Beere and Grammer Rules.</p>
            <p>It is not vnknowne to report, what a famous pottle-pot Patron you haue beene to olde Poets in your daies, and howe many pounds you haue ſpent (and as it were throwne into the fire) vpon <hi>the durt of wiſedome, called Alcumie</hi>: Yea, you are ſuch an infinite Mecaenas to learned men, that there is not that morſell of meate they can carue you, but you will eate for their ſakes and accept very thankefully. Thinke not though vnder correction of your boone companionſhip, I am diſpoſd to be a little pleaſant, I condemne you of any immoderation either in eating or drinking, for I knowe your go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement and carriage to be euery way Canonicall. Verily, verily, all poore Schollers acknowledge you as their patron, prouiditore, and ſupporter, for there cannot a threed-bare Cloake ſooner peepe forth, but you ſtrait preſſe it to be an outbrother of your bounty, three decayed Students you kept at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending vpon you a long time.</p>
            <p>Shall I preſume to dilate of the grauity of your round cap and your dud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion dagger? It is thought they will make you be calld vpon ſhortly to bee Alderman of the Stilliard. And thats well remembred, I heard ſay when this laſt Terme was remooued to Hartford, you fell into a great ſtudy and care by your ſelfe, to what place the Stilliard ſhould be remooued: I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you truely it was a deepe meditation, and ſuch as might well haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemed Eldertons Parliament of noſes to haue ſit vpon.</p>
            <p>A Tauerne in London, onely vpon the motion mourned all in blacke, and forbare to girt her temples with iuie, becauſe the grandam of good fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was like to depart from among them. And I wonder very much, that you <hi>Sampſownd</hi> not your ſelfe into a conſumption with the profound cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Diu viuas in amore iociſque,</hi> whatſoeuer you doe, beware of keeping dyet. Sloth is a ſinne, and one ſinne (as one poyſon) muſt bee expelled with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. What can he doe better that hath nothing to doe, than fall a drinking to keepe him from idlenes?</p>
            <p>Fah, me thinkes my ieaſts begin already to ſmell of the Caske, with tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſo much of this liquid prouinder.</p>
            <p>In earneſt thus: There is a <hi>Doctor and his Fart,</hi> that haue kept a foule ſtinking ſtirre in Paules Churchyard: I cry him mercie I ſlaundred him, he is ſcarſe a Doctor till he hath done his Acts: this dodipoule, this d<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>, this profeſſed poetical braggart, hath raild vppo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> mee w<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hout wit or <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> certaine foure penny-worth of Letters, and three farthing-worth of <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets: now do I meane to preſent him and <hi>Shakerley</hi> to the Queene <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:2"/>
taker for Coatch-horſes: for two that draw more equally in one Oratoriall yoke of vaine-glory there is not vnder heauen.</p>
            <p>What ſay you Maiſter <hi>Apis Lapis,</hi> will you wirh your eloquence and credit ſhield me from Carpers? Haue you any odde ſhreds of Latine to make this lettermunger a Cockeſcombe off?</p>
            <p>It ſtands you in hand to arme your ſelfe againſt him, for he ſpeaks againſt Conny-catchers, and you are a Connycatcher, as Connycatching is diuided into three parts, the <hi>Verſer,</hi> the <hi>Setter,</hi> and the <hi>Barnacle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Setter,</hi> I am ſure you are not, for you are no Muſitian: nor a <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle,</hi> for you neuer were of the order of the Barnardines: but the <hi>Verſer,</hi> I cannot acquite you of, for M. <hi>Vaux</hi> of <hi>Lambeth</hi> brings in ſore euidence of a breakefaſt you wonne of him one morning at an vnlawfull game called riming. What lies not in you to amend play the <hi>Doctor</hi> and defend.</p>
            <p>A fellow that I am to talke with by and by, beeing told that his Father was a Rope-maker, excuſed the matter after this ſort: <hi>And hath neuer ſaint had Reprobate to his Father?</hi> They are his owne wordes hee cannot goe from them. You ſee heere hee makes a <hi>Reprobate</hi> and a <hi>Ropemaker, <hi>voces conuertibiles.</hi>
               </hi> Go too, take example by him to waſh out durt with inke, &amp; runne vp to the knees in the Channell, if you bee once wetſhod. You are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt graue Doctors, and men of iudgement in both Lawes euery day. I pray aske them the queſtion in my abſence, whether ſuch a man as I haue deſcribde this <hi>Epiſtler</hi> to be, one that hath a good handſome pickerdeuant, and a pretty leg to ſtudy the Ciuill Law with, that hath made many proper rimes of the old Cutte in his daies, and deſerued infinitely of the ſtate by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolling himſelfe and his two brothers in euery booke he writes: whether (I ſay) ſuch a famous piller of the Preſſe, now in the fourteenth or fifteenth yeare of the raigne of his Rhetoricke, giuing money to haue this his illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Pamphlet of Letters printed (whereas others haue money giuen them to ſuffer themſelues to come in Print) it is not to bee counted as flat ſimony, and be liable to one and <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſame penalty.</p>
            <p>I tell you, meane to trounce him after twenty in the hundred, and haue about with him with two ſtaues and a pike for this geare.</p>
            <p>If he get any thing by the bargaine, let whatſoeuer I write henceforward be condemned to wrappe bumbaſt in.</p>
            <p>Ca<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ic<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to me good lucke, for I am reſolutely bent, the beſt bloud of the broth <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> pledge me in vineger. O would thou hadſt a quaffing bowle, which the <hi>Gawens</hi> ſcull ſhould containe a peeke, that thou mightſt ſwap off <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ary draught to the ſucceſſe of this voyage.</p>
            <p>By whatſoeuer thy viſage holdeth moſt pretious I beſeech thee, by <hi>Iohn Da<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ts</hi> ſoule, and the blew Bore in the Spittle I coniure thee, to draw out <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and giue me nothing for the Dedication of my Pamphlet.</p>
            <p>Thou art a good fellow I know, and hadſt rather ſpend ieaſts than money, Let it be the taske of thy beſt tearmes, to ſafeconduct this booke through the enemies countrey.</p>
            <p>Proceede to cheriſh thy ſurpaſſing carminicall art of memory with full cuppes (as thou doſt) let <hi>Chaucer</hi> bee newe ſcourd againſt the day of bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile, and <hi>Terence</hi> come but in now and then with the ſnuffe of a ſentence: and <hi>Dictum pu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a,</hi> Weele ſtrike it as dead as a doore naile: <hi>Haud terun<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ij estimo,</hi> We haue cats meat and dogges meat inough for theſe mungrels. Howeuer I write merrily, I loue and admire thy pleaſant witty humor, which no care or croſſe can make vnconuerſable. Still bee conſtant to thy content, loue poetry, hate pedantiſme, <hi>Vade, vale, caue ne titubes mandataque frangas.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine intirely, <hi>Tho. Naſhe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:3264:3"/>
            <head>To the Gentlemen. <hi>Readers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entlemen, the ſtrong faith you haue conceiu'd, that I would do works of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererrogation in anſwering the Doctor, hath made mee to breake my daye with other important buſines I had, and ſtand darting of quils a while like the Porpentine.</p>
            <p>I know there want not welwillers to my diſgrace, who ſay my onely Muſe is contention; and other, that with <hi>Tiberius Caeſar</hi> pretending to ſee in the darke, talke of ſtrange obiectes by them diſcouered in the night, when in truth they are nothing elſe but the glimmering of their eyes.</p>
            <p>I will not holde the candle to the Deuill, vnmaske my holyday Muſe to enuie; but if any ſuch deepe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted detracter will challenge mee to whatſoeuer quiet aduenture of Art wherein he thinkes mee leaſt conuerſant, hee ſhall finde that I am <hi>Tam Mercurio quàm Marti,</hi> a Scholler in ſome thing els but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>If idle wittes will needes tye knottes on ſmooth bulruſhes with their tongues, faith the worlde might thinke I had little to attend, if I ſhould goe about to vnlooſe them with my penne.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:3"/>I cannot tell how it comes to paſſe but in theſe ill eide daies of ours, euery man delights with <hi>Ixion</hi> to beget children of clouds, digge for Pearles in dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hils, and wreſt oyle out of iron.</p>
            <p>Poore <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe,</hi> haue they turnd to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuring booke, for there is not that line in it, with which they doo not ſeeke to raiſe vp a Ghoſt, and like the hog that conuerts the ſixth part of his meate into briſtels, ſo haue the<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>nuerted ſixe parts of my booke into bitternes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aretine</hi> in a Commedie of his, wittily complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that vpſtart Commenters, with their Annotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and gloſes, had extorted that ſenſe and Morall out of <hi>Petrarch,</hi> which if <hi>Petrarch</hi> were aliue a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Strappadoes might not make him confeſſe or ſubſcribe too; So may I complaine that raſh heads, vpſtart Interpreters, haue extorted &amp; rakte that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reuerent meaning out of my lines, which a thouſand deaths cannot make mee ere grant that I dreamd off.</p>
            <p>To them that are abuſed by their owne iealous collections and no determined treſpaſſe of mine, this aduice by the way of example will I giue.</p>
            <p>One comming to Doctour <hi>Perne</hi> on a time, and telling him hee was miſerably raild on ſuch a day in a Sermon at Saint Maries in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> I but quoth he (in his puling manner of ſpeaking) did he name me, did he name me, I warrant you goe and aske him, and hee will ſay hee meant not mee; So they that are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groundedly offended at any thing in <hi>Pierce Penni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,</hi> firſt let them looke if I did name them; if not, but the matter hangeth in ſuſpence, let them ſend to mee for my expoſition, and not buy it at the ſeconde hand, and I doe not doubt but they will be through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:4"/>Hee that wraps himſelfe in earth like the Foxe, to catch birds, may haps haue a heauy cart go ouer him before he be aware, and breake his backe.</p>
            <p>A number of Apes may get the glowworme in the night, and thinke to kindle fire with it, becauſe it gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſo, but God wote they are beguiled it proues in the end to be but fools fire, the poore worme alone with their blowing is warmed, they ſtarud for colde whiles their wood is vntoucht. Who but a Foppe wil labour to anatomize a Flye <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ables were free for any bondman to ſpeake in old time, as <hi>Aeſope</hi> for an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, their alluſion was not reſtrained to any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular humor of ſpite, but generally applyed to a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall vice. Now a man may not talke of a dog, but it is ſurmiſed he aimes at him that giueth the dog in his Creſt, hee cannot name ſtraw, but hee muſt plucke a wheate ſheaffe in pieces, <hi>Iutelligendo faciunt vt nihil intelligant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVhat euer they be that thus perſecute Art (as the Alcumiſts are ſaid to perſecute Nature) I would wiſh them to rebate the edge of their wit, and not grinde their colours ſo harde, hauing founde that which is blacke, let them not with our forenamed Gold-falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiers, ſeeke for a ſubſtance that is blacker than black, or angle for frogs in a cleare fountaine.</p>
            <p>From the admonition of theſe vncurteous miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterers. I come to <hi>The kilcow champion of the three bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi>; he forſooth wil be the firſt that ſhal giue <hi>Pierce Penileſſe</hi> a <hi>non placet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not inough that hee bepiſt his credite about twelue yeeres ago, with <hi>Three proper and wittie fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar letters,</hi> but ſtill he muſt be running on the <hi>letter,</hi> and abuſing the Queenes Engliſh without pittie or mercie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:4"/>Bee it knowne vnto you (Chriſtian Readers) this man is a foreſtaller of the market of fame, an ingroſſer of glorie, a mounte bancke of ſtrange wordes, a meere marchant of babies and conny-skins.</p>
            <p>Hold vp thy hand <hi>G. H.</hi> thou art heere indited for an incrocher vpon the fee-ſimple of the Latin, an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to Carriers, as one that takes their occupation out of their hands and doſt nothing but tranſport let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vp and downe in thy owne commendation, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiratour and practiſer to make Printers rich, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thy ſelfe ridiculous, a manifeſt briber of Booke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers and Stationers, to helpe thee to ſell away thy bookes (whoſe impreſſion thou paidſt for) that thou mayſt haue money to goe home to Trinitie Hall to diſcharge thy commons.</p>
            <p>I ſay no more but Lord haue mercie vpon thee, for thou art falne into his hands that will plague thee.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, will you be inſtructed in the quarrell that hath cauſd him lay about him with his penne and inckehorne ſo couragiouſly. About two yeeres ſince (a fatall time to familiar Epiſtles) a certayne Theologicall gimpanado, a demie diuine, no higher than a Tailors preſſing iron, brother to this huge booke-beare, that writes himſelfe <hi>One of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour Iustinians Courtiers,</hi> tooke vppon him to ſet his foote to mine, and ouer-crow mee with comparatiue tearmes. I proteſt I neuer turnd vp any cowſheard to looke for this ſcarabe flye. I had no conceit as then of diſcouering a breed of fooles in the three brothers bookes: marry when I beheld ordinance planted on edge of the pulpit againſt me, &amp; that there was no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy but the blind Vicar would needs let flie at me with his Churchdore keies, &amp; curſe me with bel, book and candle, becauſe in my Alphabet of Idiots I had
<pb facs="tcp:3264:5"/>
ouer-skipt the Hs, what could I doe but draw vppon him with my penne, and defende my ſelfe with it and a paper buckler as well as I might.</p>
            <p>Say I am as verie a Turke as hee that three yeeres ago ranne vpon ropes, if euer I ſpeld eyther his or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of his kindreds name in reproch, before hee barkt againſt mee as one of the enemies of the Lambe of God, and fetcht alluſions out of the Buttery to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe mee.</p>
            <p>Heere beginneth the fray. I vpbraid godly predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation with his wicked conuerſation, I ſquirt inke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his decayed eyes with iniquitie to mend their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſed ſight, that they may a little better deſcend into my ſchollerſhip and learning. The Eccleſiaſtical duns in ſtead of recouery waxeth ſtarke blind thereby (as a preſeruatiue to ſome, is poyſon to others) hee gets an olde Fencer his brother to be reuengd on me for my Phiſicke; who flouriſhing about my eares with his two hand ſworde of Oratory and Poetry, peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhakes ſome of the ruſt of it on my ſhoulders, but otherwiſe ſtrikes mee not but with the ſhadowe of it, which is no more than a flappe with the falſe ſcabberd of contumelie: whether am I in this caſe to arme my ſelfe againſt his intent of iniurie, or ſitte ſtill with my finger in my mouth, in hope to bee one of ſimplicities martyrs.</p>
            <p>A queſt of honorable minded Caualiers go vppon it, and if they ſhall find by the Law of armes or of ale, that I beeing firſt prouokt, am to bee inioynde to the peace, or be ſworne true ſeruant to cowardize &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, when wrong preſſeth mee to the warres; then wil I bind my ſelfe prentiſe to a Cobler, and freſh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlay all thoſe writings of mine that haue trodde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:5"/>Be aduertiſed (gentle audience) that the <hi>Doctors</hi> proceedings haue thruſt vpon mee this ſowterly Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor, who firſt contriuing his confutation in a ſhort Pamphlet of ſix leaues like a paire of ſummer pumps: afterward (winter growing on) clapt a paire of dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoales on it like a good husband, added eight ſheets more, and prickt thoſe ſheets or ſoales as full of the hob-nayles of reprehenſion as they could ſticke.</p>
            <p>It is not thoſe his new clowted ſtartops iwis, that ſhall carry him out of the durt.</p>
            <p>Sweet Gentlemen, be but indifferent, and you ſhal ſee mee deſperate. Heere lies my hatte, and there my cloake, to which I reſemble my two Epiſtles, being the vpper garments of my booke, as the other of my body: Saint Fame for mee, and thus I runne vpon him.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Naſhe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:3264:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3264:6"/>
            <head>The foure Letters Confuted.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Abriel</hi> and not onely <hi>Gabriel,</hi> but <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brieliſſime Gabriel,</hi> no Angell but AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GELOS, id eſt, <hi>Nuntius,</hi> a Fawnegueſt Meſſenger twixt Maiſter <hi>Bird</hi> and Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Demetrius</hi>: Behold, here ſtands he that will make it good on thy foure Letters bodie, that thou art a filthy vaine foole. Thy booke I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend; as very well printed: and like wondrous well, becauſe all men diſlike it.</p>
            <p>I agree with thee that there are in it <hi>ſome matters of Note,</hi> for there are a great many barefoote rimes in it that goe as iumpe as a Fiddle with euery ballet-makers note: and if according to their manner you had tun'd them ouer the head it had beene nere the worſe, for by that meanes you might haue had your name chaunted in euery corner of the ſtreete, then the which there can be nothing more <hi>melodiouſlie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doulce</hi> to your <hi>deuine Entelechy.</hi> O they would haue trowld off brauely to the tune of <hi>O man in Despera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and like <hi>Marenzos</hi> Madrigals, the mournefull note naturally haue affected rhe miſerable Dittie.</p>
            <p>Doe you knowe your owne misbegotten bodgery
<pb facs="tcp:3264:7"/>
               <hi>Entelechy</hi> and <hi>addoulce.</hi> VVith theſe two Hermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrodite phraſes, being halfe Latin and halfe Engliſh, haſt thou puld out the very guts of the inkehorne.</p>
            <div type="dialogue">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Letters.</speaker>
                  <p>To all curteous mindes that will vouchſafe the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Comment.</speaker>
                  <p>In their abſence this be deliuered to <hi>Megge Curtis</hi> in Shorditch to ſtop muſtard pots with.</p>
               </sp>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <head>The particular Contents.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A Praeface to courteous mindes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>As much to ſay, as Preface, much good do it you would it were better for you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A Letter to M.</hi> Emanuel Demetrius, <hi>with a ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net thereto annexed.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That is, as it were a purgation vpon a vomit, bus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins vpon pantophles.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A Letter to M.</hi> Bird.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Or little matter wrapt vp in many words.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>A Letter to euerie fauorable and indifferent Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Id eſt,</hi> An exhortation to all Readers, that they ſhall reade nothing but his works.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Another letter to the ſame extorted after the reſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>By interpretation, a Letter whereof his inuention had a hard ſtoole, and yet it was for his caſe, though not for his honeſtie: and ſo forth, as the Text ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you at large.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:3264:7"/>
            <head>Heere beginneth the firſt Epiſtle and firſt Booke of <hi>Orator Gabriell to the Cati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linaries or Philippicks.</hi>
            </head>
            <argument>
               <p>Wherein is <hi>diuulged,</hi> that venum is venum and will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>infect, that that which is done, cannot <hi>(de facto)</hi> be vndone, that fauour is a curteous Reader, and <hi>G.H.</hi> your thankfull debter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Comment vpon the Text.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He learned Orator in this Epiſtle <hi>taketh preciſe order</hi> he will not be too eloquent and yet it ſhall be (L,) <hi>as well for enditing vnworthie to be publiſhed, as for publiſhing vnworthie to be endited.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>C.</hi> He had many aduerſaries in thoſe times that he wrote, amongſt the which Cloth-breeches and Vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet-breeches (his fathers pouerty, and his owne pride were none of the meaneſt.)</p>
            <p>After them ſtart vp one <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe,</hi> and hee likewiſe was a ſtumbling blocke in his way. (Penurie not long tarries after pride; pray all the ropes in <hi>Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron Walden</hi> that I do not propheſie,) Amen, Amen, quoth M. <hi>Bird</hi> and M. <hi>Demetrius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee forbeares to ſpeake much in this place of the one or the other, <hi>becauſe his letters are more forvvard to accuſe them than their owne books to condemne them</hi>; yet for a touch by the way, hee talks that Greene is no
<pb facs="tcp:3264:8"/>
liuerey for this winter, <hi>it is pitifully blaſted and faded in euerie meade</hi> by the ſtrong breath of his barbariſme.</p>
            <p>Hee hath a twitch at <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe</hi> too, at the parting ſtile, and tearms him <hi>the Deuils Orator by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, and his Dames Poet by practiſe:</hi> wherein mee thinks (the ſurreuerence of his works not impaired) he hath verie highly ouerſhotte himſelfe: for no more is <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe</hi> to be cald the Deuils Orator for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Supplication to the Deuill, than hee is to bee helde for a Rhethoritian, for ſetting foorth <hi>Gabrielis Scuruei Rhetor,</hi> wherein hee thought to haue knockt out the braines of poore <hi>Tullies Orator,</hi> but in veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie did nothing elſe but gather a flaunting vnſauory fore-horſe noſegay out of his well furniſhed gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
            <p>The aduanceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Deuils Oratorſhip, which he aſcribeth to <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe,</hi> me thinks had beene a fit place for his Doctorſhip, when hee miſt the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torſhip of the Vniuerſitie, of which in the ſequele of his booke he moſt ſlanderouſly complaineth. Doctor <hi>Perne, Greene,</hi> no dead man he ſpareth.</p>
            <p>What he ſhould <hi>ſubandi</hi> by his <hi>Dames Poet,</hi> I ſcarſe apprehend, except this, that <hi>Pierce</hi> his Father was <hi>Dame Lawſ.</hi> Poet, and writte many goodly ſtories of her in <hi>An Almond for Parrat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thoſe that will take a Lecture in our Orators let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, muſt not <hi>read, excuſe, commend, credite or beleeue anie approoued truth in</hi> Pierce Pennileſſe, eſpecially if it be any thing that vpbraideth the great Baboune brother.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hee will ſtoppe the beginning, id eſt,</hi> when hee hath come behind a man and broke his head, ſeeke to bind him to the good a bearing, <hi>or els the ende were like to proue pernitious and perillous</hi> to his confuſion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:8"/>Somewhat hee mutters of <hi>defamation and iuſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation,</hi> &amp; what a hell it is for him that hath built his heauen in vaine-glory, to bee puld by the ſleeue, and bidde <hi>Reſpice funem,</hi> looke backe to his Fathers houſe; but I ouerſlippe it as friuolous, becauſe all the world knowes him better than he knowes himſelfe, &amp; though he play the Phariſie neuer ſo in iuſtifiyng his owne innocence, theres none will beleeue him.</p>
            <p>Let this bee ſpoken once for all, as I haue a ſoule to ſaue, till this day in all my life with tongue nor penne did I euer in the leaſt worde or tittle derogate from the Doctor. If his brother (without any former pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation on my part God is my witneſſe) rayld on me groſſely, expreſly namde mee, compard me to <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,</hi> indeuord to take from mee all eſtimation of Arte or witte, haue I not cauſe to beſtirre mee?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gabriell,</hi> I will beſtirre mee, for all like an Alehouſe Knight thou crau'ſt of <hi>Iustice to do thee reaſon</hi>; as for <hi>impudencie and calumny,</hi> I returne them in thy face, that in one booke of tenne ſheets of paper, haſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht aboue two hundred lies.</p>
            <p>Had they been wittie lies, or merry lies, they would neuer haue greeu'd mee: but palpable lies, damned lies, lies as big as one of the Guardes chynes of beefe, who can abide?</p>
            <p>Ile make thee of my counſaile, becauſe I loue thee (not:) when I was in Cambridge and but a childe, I was indifferently perſwaded of thee: mee thought by thy apparell and thy gate thou ſhouldſt haue beene a fine fellow: Little did I ſuſpect that thou wert bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>Io. Paean</hi> (whom inwardly I alwaies grudgd at for writing againſt <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) or any of the Hs of Hempe hall, but a Caualier of a clean contrary houſe, now thou haſt quite ſpoild thy ſelfe, from the foote to
<pb facs="tcp:3264:9"/>
the head I can tell how thou art faſhioned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Teterrime frater,</hi> and not <hi>fraterrime frater,</hi> maiſt thou verie wofully exclaime, for in helping him thou haſt crackt thy credit through the ring, made thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famie currant as farre as the Queenes coyne goes.</p>
            <p>But it may be thou haſt a ſider cloke for this quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, thou wilt obiect thy Father was abuſd, &amp; that made thee write. What by mee, or <hi>Greeue,</hi> or both?</p>
            <p>If by <hi>Greene</hi> and not mee, thou ſhouldſt haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten againſt <hi>Greene</hi> and not mee. If by both, I will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere for both, but not by both, therefore I will aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere but for one.</p>
            <p>Giue an inſtance if thou canſt for thy life, wherin in any leafe of <hi>Pierce Penileſſe</hi> I had ſo much as halfe a ſillables relation to thee, or offred one iot of indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to thy Father, more than naming the greateſt dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie he hath, when for varietie of Epithites I calde thy brother <hi>the ſonne of a Ropemaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſhall haue a good ſonne of you anone, if you be aſhamd of your fathers occupation: ah thou wilt nere thriue, that art beholding to a trade, and canſt not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide to heare of it.</p>
            <p>Thou doſt liue by the gallows, &amp; wouldſt not haue a ſhooe to put on thy foot if thy father had no traffike with the hangman. Had I a Ropemaker to my father, &amp; ſome body had caſt it in my teeth. I would foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with haue writ in praiſe of Ropemakers, &amp; prou'd it by ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſillogiſtry to be one of the 7. liberal ſciences.</p>
            <p>Somewhat I am priuie to the cauſe of <hi>Greenes</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueighing againſt the three brothers. Thy hot-ſpirited brother <hi>Richard</hi> (a notable ruffian with his pen) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing firſt tooke vpon him in his blundring Perſiual to play the Iacke of both ſides twixt <hi>Martin</hi> and vs, and ſnarld priuily at <hi>Pap-hatchet, Paſquill,</hi> &amp; others, that
<pb facs="tcp:3264:9"/>
oppoſde themſelues againſt the open ſlaunder of that mightie platformer of Atheiſme, preſently after drib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed forth another fooles bolt, a booke I ſhoulde ſay, which he chriſtened <hi>The Lamhe of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That booke was a learned booke, a labourd booke; for three yere before he put it in print, he had preacht it all without booke.</p>
            <p>I my ſelfe haue ſome of it in a booke of Setmons that my Tutor at Cambridge made mee gather euery Sunday. Then being very yoong, I counted it the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecteſt and frothieſt forme of Diuinitie that came in that place. Now more confirmed in age and Art, I confirme my ill opinion of it.</p>
            <p>Neither do I vrge this as if it were a hainous thing for a man to put ſermons in print after hee preacht them, but obſerue the proud humor of the pert Didi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, that thinks nothing hee ſpeakes but deſerues to be put in print, and ſpeakes not that ſentence in the Pulpit, which before he rough-hewes not ouer with his penne. Beſides, I taxe him for turning an olde coate (like a Broker) and ſelling it for a new.</p>
            <p>Theſe and a thouſand more imperfections might haue beene buried with his bookes in the bottome of a drie-fatte, and there ſlept quietly amongſt the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings of the Preſſe, if in his Epiſtle he had not beene ſo arrogantly cenſoriall.</p>
            <p>Not mee alone did hee reuile and dare to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, but g<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ickt at <hi>Pap-hatchet</hi> once more, and miſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med all our other Poets and writers about London, piperly make-plaies and make-bates.</p>
            <p>Hence <hi>Greene,</hi> beeing chiefe agent for the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie (for hee writ more than foure other, how well I will not ſay: but <hi>Sat citò, ſi ſat benè</hi>) tooke occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to canuaze him a little in his Cloth-breeches
<pb facs="tcp:3264:10"/>
and Veluet breeches, and becauſe by ſome probable collections hee geſt the elder brothers hand was in it, he coupled them both in one yoake, and to fulfill the prouerbe <hi>Tria ſunt omnia</hi> thruſt in the third brother who made a perfect parriall of Pamphleters.</p>
            <p>About ſome ſeauen or eight lines it was which hath pluckt on an inuectiue of ſo many leaues. Had hee liu'd <hi>Gabriel,</hi> and thou ſhouldſt ſo vnarteficially and odiouſly libeld againſt him as thou haſt done, he would haue made thee an example of ignominy to all ages that are to come, and driuen thee to eate thy owne booke butterd, as I ſawe him make an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parriter once in a Tauern eate his Citation waxe and all, very handſomly ſeru'd twixt two diſhes.</p>
            <p>Out vppon thee for an arrant dog-killer, ſtrike a man when he is dead,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So Hares may pull dead Lions by the beards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Memorandum,</hi> I borrowed this ſentence out of a Play. The Theater Poets hall, hath many more ſuch prouerbes to perſecute thee with, becauſe thou haſt ſo ſcornefully derided their profeſſion, and deſpite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully maligned honeſt ſports.</p>
            <p>Before I vnbowell the leane Carcaſe of thy book any further, Ile drinke one cup of lambſwooll, <hi>to the Lambe of God and his enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt foure leaues of it. I haue ſingled out theſe Godly and fruitfull obſeruations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Noble Lord I doe it euen vpon former premiſſes, not for any future conſequents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My booke is not worthy of ſo honorable ſpecialitie as your Patronage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will not proſecute it with Theologicall peculiars, but from the mouth of the ſword I ſpeake, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The hearts of the wicked pant, their ſpirits faile them,
<pb facs="tcp:3264:10"/>
they may well call for butter out of a Lordlie diſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You that bee gentle Readers doe you not laugh at this Lawiers engliſh <hi>of former premiſſes and future conſequents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O finicallitie <hi>your Patronages ſpeciallitie,</hi> but if he proſecute it with <hi>Theologicall peculiars,</hi> we muſt needs thruſt him <hi>inter oues &amp; boues, &amp; reliqua pecora campi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the mouth of the ſword I ſpeake it, <hi>that but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of a Lordly diſh</hi> is but lewd diet for the Pulpit.</p>
            <p>But this is not halfe the littour of inckehorniſme, that thoſe foure pages haue pigd. I muſt tell you of the <hi>Octonarium of Ramus, the Seſquiamus of Phrigius, the Carthuſianiſme of Gulielmus Rikel, of Annals Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries, Chronologies &amp; Tropologicall ſchoolemen, The Abetilis of the Aethiopians or Pretoioannans, of Gulielmus minatenſis, &amp; S. Ierome allegorized &amp; Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, Lyra, Gryſon, Porta, Pantaleon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which hee reckons vp to make the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue he hath read much but alleadgeth nothing out of them: Nor I thinke on my conſcience euer read or knew what they meane, but as he hath ſtole them by the wholeſale out of ſome Bookſellers Catalogue, or a table of Tractats.</p>
            <p>Here are ſome of his profounde Annotations, <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob tooke</hi> Leah <hi>for his bedfellowe in the darke by night in ſteede of</hi> Rachell, <hi>whereby I learne to buy my wife can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to goe to bed withall, and admit her not by darke but by light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Iacob <hi>was deceiued by</hi> Labans <hi>words</hi>: ergo, <hi>Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are better than bils, and we muſt belieue no man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he will waxe and multiplie in words, and call inke &amp; parchment to witnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Iacob <hi>laide pilled rods with white ſtrakes in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring places of the ſheepe, whereby I note that in carnal
<pb facs="tcp:3264:11"/>
mixture the ſenſes are opened.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Iudge you that be the Fathers of the Church whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be fit matter to edifie or no.</p>
            <p>It was not for nothing brother Richard that <hi>Greene</hi> told you you kiſt your Pariſhioners wiues with holy kiſſes, for you that wil talk <hi>of opening the ſenſes by car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal mixture</hi> (the very act of lecherie) in a Theological Treatiſe, and in the Pulpit, I am afraide in a priuater place you will practiſe as mueh as you ſpeake. <hi>Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes rarò niſi male locuti malè faciunt. Olet hïrcum, olet hircum,</hi> anie modeſt eare would abhorre to heare it.</p>
            <p>Farewell vncleane Vicar, and God make thee an honeſt man, for thou art too baudy for mee to deale withall.</p>
            <p>It followes in the Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To my verie good friend Maiſter</hi> Emanuell Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trius.</p>
            <p>This Letter of M. <hi>Bird</hi> to M. <hi>Demetrius,</hi> ſhoulde ſeeme by all reference or collation of ſtiles, to bee a Letter which M. <hi>Birds</hi> ſecretarie <hi>Doctour Gabriell</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited for him in his owne praiſe, and got him to ſette hand to when he had done. Or rather it is no letter, but a certificate (ſuch as Rogues haue) from the head men of the Pariſh where hee was borne, <hi>that</hi> Gabriel <hi>is an excellent generall Scholler, and his Father of good behauiour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We will not beleeue it except wee ſee the Towne ſeale ſette to it: but ſay wee ſhould beleeue it, what doth it make for thee? Haue the Towneſmen of <hi>Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron Waldon</hi> euer heard thee preach, that they ſhould commend thee for an excellent generall ſcholler? or (becauſe thou profeſſeſt thy ſelf a Ciuilian? haſt thou ſollicited any of their cauſes in the bawdy Courtes therabouts. If not, go your wayes a dolt as you came,
<pb facs="tcp:3264:11"/>
Maiſter <hi>Birdes</hi> Letter ſhall not repriue you from the ladder.</p>
            <p>But Veluet-breeches and Cloth-breeches (by the iudgement of the beſt man of none of the leaſt towns in Eſſex) <hi>is a fantasticall and fond Dialogue, and one of the most licentious intollerable inuectiues that euer hee read.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In it is abuſed an auncient neighbour of his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How is he abuſed?</p>
            <p>In ſtead of his name, hee is called by the craft hee gets his liuing with.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He hath borne office in</hi> VValden <hi>aboue twenty yere ſince (hoc est</hi> had the keeping of the Towne ſtocke, <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias</hi> the ſtocks) <hi>Ergo</hi> he is no Rope-maker.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He hath maintaind foure ſonnes at Cambridge: Ergo Greene</hi> is a lewd fellow to ſay he gets his liuing back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Three of his ſonnes vniuerſally ridiculouſlie reputed of</hi> (for inamoratos on their owne works) <hi>in both <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities and the whole Realme.</hi> The fourth is ſhrunke in the w<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ting, or elſe the Print ſhoulde haue heard of him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>One of the three</hi> (whom the <hi>Quip</hi> entitles the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition) <hi>returning ſicke from Norwitch to Linne in Iulie laſt,</hi> was paſt writing any more Almanackes, before <hi>Greene</hi> ere imagined God had thought ſo well of him to take him to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Liuer post quieſcat.</hi> Mother Liuers of Newington is a better fortune-teller than he was a Phiſition.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:3264:12"/>
            <head>A Daſh through the dudgen</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Sonnet againſt <hi>Greene.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Put vp thy ſmiter O gentle Peter,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Author and halter make but ill meeter.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I ſcorne to anſwer thy miſhapen rime,</l>
                  <l>Blocks haue cald ſchollers bayards ere this time.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I would trot a falſe gallop through the reſt of his ragged Verſes, but that if I ſhould retort his time dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell aright, I muſt make my verſes (as he doth his) run hobling like a Brewers Cart vpon the ſtones, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue no length in their feete, which were <hi>abſurdum per abſurdius,</hi> to infect my vaine with his imitation.</p>
            <p>The Analaſis of the whole is this: an olde mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical meeter-munger would faine raile if he had anie witte. If <hi>Greene</hi> were <hi>dogge-ſicke and brain-ſicke,</hi> ſure he (poore ſecular Satiriſt) is dolt-ſicke and brainleſſe that with the toothleſſe gums of his Poetry ſo betug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth a dead man.</p>
            <p>But I cannot be induced to beleue a graue man of his ſort ſhould be ere ſo <hi>rauingly</hi> bent: when all coms to all, <hi>ſhorteſt vowels and longeſt mutes</hi> will bewray it to bee a webbe of your owne loomes M. <hi>Gabriel,</hi> you <hi>mute</hi> foorth many ſuch phraſes in the courſe of your booke, which I will point at as I paſſe by.</p>
            <p>I will not robbe you of your due commendation in any thing: in this Sonnet you haue counterfeited the ſtile of the olde Vice in the Morrals, as right vp and downe as may be.</p>
            <q>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Let.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Greene the Connycatcher of this dreame the author,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For his daintie deuiſe deſerueth the hauter.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3264:12"/>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice.</speaker>
                  <l>Hey nan a non ſir, ſoft let mee make water,</l>
                  <l>VVhip it to go, Ile kiſſe my maiſters daughter.</l>
                  <l>Tum diddy, tum da, falangtedo diddle,</l>
                  <l>Sol la me fa ſol, conatus in fiddle.</l>
               </sp>
            </q>
            <p>I am afraide your <hi>Doctors fart</hi> will fall out to be a fatall foyſt to your breeches, if we followe you at the hard heeles as we haue begun.</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt not breath a whit, trip and goe, turne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a new leafe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maiſter</hi> Bird <hi>in the abſence of M.</hi> Demetrius. Perge porrò. <hi>I found his wife curteous,</hi> barlady ſir but that is ſuſpitious.</p>
            <p>A woman is well holpen vp that does you any cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie in the abſence of her husband, when you cannot keepe it to yourſelfe, but you muſt blab it in print.</p>
            <p>If it were any other but Miſtris <hi>Demetrius</hi> (whome I haue heard to be a modeſt ſober woman, and indued with many vertues) I would play vpon it a litle more. In regard that ſhee is ſo, I forbeare; and craue pardon in that I haue ſpoken ſo much.</p>
            <p>Yet would I haue her vnderſtand, how well <hi>the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſcholler</hi> her gueſt hath rewarded hir for his kind entertainment, by bringing her name in queſtion in print.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Bird</hi> and <hi>Demetrius,</hi> I knowe neither of you by ſight, but this Ile ſay, being of that welth you are, you had better haue ſpent a great deale of money, than come in the mouth of this baſe companion.</p>
            <p>VVhat reaſon haue I (ſeeing your names ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed as his bolſterer, in a matter of defame that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes mee) but to go through ſtitch with you as well as him.</p>
            <p>He thinks to ouer-beare vs as poore beggers with
<pb facs="tcp:3264:13"/>
the great oſtentation of your rich acquaintance.</p>
            <p>Lette all Noblemen take heede how they giue this <hi>Thraſo</hi> the leaſt becke or countenance, for if they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe but halfe a glaunce on him, heleſtraight put it verie ſolemnly in print, and make it ten times more than it is.</p>
            <p>Ile tell you a merry ieaſt.</p>
            <p>The time was when this <hi>Timothie Tiptoes</hi> made a Latine Oration to her Maieſtie. Her Highnes as ſhee is vnto all her ſubiects moſt gratious: ſo to ſchollers ſhe is more louing and affable than any Prince vnder heauen. In which reſpect, of her owne vertue and not his deſert, it pleaſed hir ſo to humble the height of hir iudgement, as to grace him a little whiles he was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing, by theſe or ſuch like tearmes. <hi>Tis a good pretie fellow, a lookes like an Italian,</hi> and after hee had concluded, to call him to kiſſe her royall hand. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon hee goes home to his ſtudie all intraunced, and writes a whole volume of Verſes; firſt <hi>De vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu Itali,</hi> of the countenance of the Italian; and then <hi>De oſculo manus,</hi> of his kiſſing the Queenes hande. VVhich two Latin Poems he publiſht in a booke of his cald <hi>Aedes <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aldinenſes,</hi> proclaiming thereby (as it were to England, Fraunce, Italie and Spaine, what fauour hee was in with her Maieſtie.</p>
            <p>I diſmiſſe this <hi>Parentheſis,</hi> and <hi>come to his next bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe,</hi> which indeede is his firſt buſineſſe: for tyll <hi>Greene</hi> awakte him out of his ſelfe admiring contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, hee had nothing to doe, but walke vnder the Ewe tree at Trinitie hall, and ſay:
<q>
                  <l>What may I call this tree, an Ewe tree O bonny Ewe tree,</l>
                  <l>Needes to thy boughs will bow this knee, and vaile my bonne to,</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:13"/>Or make verſes of weathercocks on the top of ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, as he did once of the weathercocke of Alhallows in Cambridge:
<q>
                  <l>O thou weathercocke that ſtands on the top of the Church of Alhallows,</l>
                  <l>Come thy waies down if thou durſt for thy crowne and take the wall on vs.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>O Heatheniſh and Pagan Hexamiters, come thy waies down fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy <hi>Doctourſhip,</hi> &amp; learne thy Primer of Poetry ouer again, for certainly thy pen is in ſtate of a Reprobate with all men of iudgement and rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning.</p>
            <p>Come thy waies downe from thy Doctourſhip ſaid I? <hi>Erraui demens</hi> thou neuer wentſt vp to it yet.</p>
            <p>Fie on hypocriſie and Diſſimulation, that men ſhould make themſelues better than they are.</p>
            <p>Alas a Gods will thou art but a plaine motheaten Maiſter of Art, and neuer pollutedſt thy ſelfe with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny plaiſter of Doctourſhip.</p>
            <p>Liſt Pauls Churchyard (the peruſer of euerie mans works &amp; Exchange of all Authors) you are a many of you honeſt fellows, and fauour men of wit.</p>
            <p>So it is that a good Gowne and a well pruned paire of mouſtachios, hauing ſtudied ſixteene yeare to make thirteene ill engliſh Hexameters, came to the Vniuerſity Court <hi>regentium &amp; non</hi> to ſue for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to carry two faces in a hoode, they not vſing to deny honour to any man that deſerued it, bad him performe all the Scholler like ceremonies and diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue right appertaining thereto, and he ſhould bee inſtalled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> he likt none of that.</p>
            <p>A ſtripling that hath an indifferent prety ſtocke, of reputation abroade in the worlde already, and ſome credit amongſt his neighbours as he thinketh, would
<pb facs="tcp:3264:14"/>
be loth to ieoperd all at one throwe at the dice.</p>
            <p>If hee ſhould haue diſputed for his degree, diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>in arenam &amp; puluerem Philoſophicum,</hi> and haue beene foild, <hi>Aih me quoth</hi> VVit <hi>in lamentable ſort,</hi> what ſhould haue become of him, hee might haue beene ſhot through ere hee were aware with a Sillo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme.</p>
            <p>No point, <hi>Ergo,</hi> it were wiſely done of goodman <hi>Boores</hi> ſonne if he ſhould goe to the warres for honor and returne with a wodden legge, when he may buy a Captaineſhip at home better cheape.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pumps and Pantofles</hi> becauſe they were well blackt and gliſtered iolly freſhly on it, being rubd ouer with inke, had their grace at length to be Doctour <hi>Ea lege,</hi> that they ſhould do their acts (that is, performe more than they were able)</p>
            <p>Curſt be the time that euer there were any obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions made with conditions, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde habeas quaerit nemo ſed oportet habere,</hi> Howe Dorbell comes to bee Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour none asks, but Doctour hee muſt bee to make him right worſhipfull.</p>
            <p>Acts are but idle wordes, and the Scripture ſaith, wee muſt giue account for euery idle word.</p>
            <p>Pumps and Pantofles ſweare they will iet away with a cleare conſcience at the daie of iudgement, and therfore do no Acts, giue no offence with idle words, onelie like a Hauke let flie at a Partridge, that turnes the taile and betakes her to a walnut-tree, ſo to Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford they trudge hauing their grace <hi>ad disputandum,</hi> and there are confirmed in the ſame degree they took at Cambridge: which is as if a Prentiſe heere in London, as ſoone as hee is enrould, ſhould runne to ſome ſuch Towne as Ipſwich, and there craue to haue his Freedome confirmd as of London, which in truth
<pb facs="tcp:3264:14"/>
is no Freedome becauſe hee hath not ſeru'd out his prentiſhip.</p>
            <p>Truſt mee not for a dodkin, if there bee not all the Doctourſhip hee hath, yet will the inſolent inke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horne worme write himſelfe Right worſhipfull of the Lawes, and perſonate this man and that man, calling him <hi>my good friend Maister Doctour</hi> at euery word.</p>
            <p>Doctour or no Doctour <hi>Greene ſurfeted not of Pickled hearing but of an exceeding feare</hi> of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hee offred in his extreameſt want twentie ſhillings to the Printer to leaue out the matter of the three bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Haud facile credo,</hi> I am ſure the Printer beeing of that honeſtie that I take him for, will not affirme it.</p>
            <p>Marry this I muſt ſay, there was a learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour of Phiſicke (to whom Greene in his ſickeneſſe ſent for counſaile) that hauing read ouer the booke of Veluet breeches and Clothbreeches, and laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing merrilie at the three brothers legend, wild Green in any caſe either to mittigate it or leaue it out: Not for any extraordinarie account hee made of the fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternitie of fooles, but for one of them was procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the ſame facultie of Phiſicke hee profeſt, and willinglie hee would haue none of that excellent cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ill ſpoken off.</p>
            <p>This was the cauſe of the altring of it, the feare of his Phiſitions diſpleaſure, not any feare elſe.</p>
            <p>I keepe your <hi>conſcious minde</hi> with all other odde ends of your halfe fac'd engliſh till the full concluſion of my booke, where in an honorable <hi>Index</hi> they ſhall be placed according to their degree and ſegnioritie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:15"/>We are to vexe you mightely for plucking <hi>Elderton</hi> out of the aſhes of his Ale, and not letting him inioy his nappie muſe of ballad making to himſelfe, but now when he is as dead as dead beere, you muſt bee finding fault with the brewing of his meeters.</p>
            <p>Hough <hi>Thomas Delone, Phillip Stubs, Robert Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min,</hi> &amp;c. Your father <hi>Elderton</hi> is abus'd. Reuenge, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge on courſe paper and want of matter, that hath moſt ſacriligiouſly contaminated the diuine ſpirit &amp; quinteſſence of a penny a quart.</p>
            <p>Helter skelter, feare no colours, courſe him, trounce him, one cup of perfect bonauenture licour will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire you with more wit and Schollerſhip than hee hath thruſt into his whole packet of Letters.</p>
            <p>You that bee lookers on perhaps imagine I talke like a merry man, and not in good earneſt when I ſay that <hi>Eldertons</hi> ghoſt and <hi>Gabriel</hi> are at ſuch ods: but then you knowe nothing, for there hath beene mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous emulation twixt <hi>Elderton</hi> and him time out of mind. Yea, they were riuals in riming foure yeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the great froſt. Hee expreſſely writ againſt him, 1580. <hi>In his ſhort but ſharpe and learned iudgement of Earthquakes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Broome boyes, and cornecutters, (or whatſoeuer trade is more contemptible) come not in his way, ſtand fortie foote from the execution place of his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, for elſe in the full tide of his ſtandiſh he will car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie your occupations handſmooth out of towne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, beſmeare them, drowne them, downe the riuer they goe <hi>Priuily</hi> to the Ile of Dogges with his Pamphlets.</p>
            <p>O it is a peſtilent libeller againſt beggers, hee meanes ſhortly to ſet foorth a booke cald his Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe vpon Paris Garden, wherein hee will ſo tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb facs="tcp:3264:15"/>
with the interpreter of the Puppits, and betouſe Harry of Tame and great Ned, that Titius <hi>ſhall not vpbraid</hi> Caius <hi>with euerie thing and nothing, nor</hi> Zoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus <hi>anie more flurt</hi> Homer, <hi>nor</hi> Therſites <hi>fling at</hi> Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memnon.</p>
            <p>Holla, holla, holla, <hi>flurt, fling,</hi> what reaſty Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke haue we here? certes, certes brother <hi>hoddy doddy,</hi> your penne is a coult by cockes body.</p>
            <p>As touching the libertie of Orators and Poets, I will conferre with thee ſomewhat grauely, although thou beeſt a gooſe-cappe and haſt no iudgement.</p>
            <p>A libertie they haue thou ſayſt, <hi>but no liberty with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bounds, no licence without limitation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ieſu what miſter wonders doſt thou tell vs? euery thing hath an end, and a pudding hath two.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That libertie Poets of late in their inuectiues haue exceeded,</hi> they haue borne their ſword vp, where it is not lawfull for a poynado that is but the page of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſſe to intermeddle.</p>
            <p>Thou bringſt in <hi>Mother Hubbard</hi> for an inſtance. Go no further, but here confeſſe thy ſelfe a flat nodg-ſcombe before all this congregation; for thou haſt dealt by thy friend as homely as thou didſt by thy father.</p>
            <p>Who publikely accuſde or of late brought <hi>Mother Hubbard</hi> into queſtion, that thou ſhouldſt by rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall rekindle againſt him the ſparkes of diſpleaſure that were quenched?</p>
            <p>Forgot hee the <hi>pure ſanguine of his Fairy Queene</hi> ſayſt thou?</p>
            <p>A <hi>pure ſanguine</hi> ſot art thou, that in vaine-glory to haue <hi>Spencer</hi> known for thy friend, and that thou haſt ſome intereſt in him, cenſereſt him worſe than his deadlieſt enemie would do.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:16"/>If any man were vndeſeruedly toucht in it, thou haſt reuiued his diſgrace that was ſo toucht in it, by renaming it, when it was worn out of al mens mouths and minds.</p>
            <p>Beſides, whereas before I thought it a made mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſome malitious moralizers againſt him, and no ſubſtance of ſlaunder in truth, now when thou (that proclaimeſt thy ſelfe the only familiar of his boſome, and therefore ſhouldſt know his ſecretes) giues it out in print that he ouerſhotte himſelfe therein; it cannot chuſe but be ſuſpected to be ſo indeed.</p>
            <p>Immortall <hi>Spencer,</hi> no frailtie hath thy ſame, but the imputation of this Idiots friendſhip: vpon an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted <hi>Pegaſus</hi> ſhould thy gorgeous attired <hi>Fayrie Queene</hi> ride triumphant through all reports domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but that this mud-born bubble, this bile on the browe of the Vniuerſitie, this bladder of pride newe blowne, challengeth ſome intereſt in her proſperitie.</p>
            <p>Of pitch who hath any vſe at all, ſhall be abuſd by it in the end.</p>
            <p>High graſſe that floriſheth for a ſeaſon on the houſe toppe, fadeth before the harueſt cals for it, and maye well make a fayre ſhewe, but hath no ſweetneſſe in it. Such is this Aſſe in preſent, this groſſe painted image of pride, who would faine counterfeite a good witte, but ſcornfull pittie his beſt patron, knows it becomes him as ill, as an vnweldy Elephant to imitate a whelpe in his wantonnes.</p>
            <p>I wote not how it fals out, but his inuention is ouer-weapond; he hath ſome good words, but he cannot writhe them and toſſe them to and fro nimbly, or ſo bring them about, that hee maye make one ſtreight thruſt at his enemies face.</p>
            <p>Coldly and dally <hi>idem per idem</hi> who cannot indite?
<pb facs="tcp:3264:16"/>
but with life and ſpirit to limne deadnes it ſelfe, <hi>Hoc eſt Oratoris proprium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>L. <hi>Inuectiues by fauour haue beene too bolde, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires by vſurpation too preſumptuous.</hi> What pleaſure brings this to the reader? Iacke of the Falcon in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge can ſay as much and giue no reaſon for it.</p>
            <p>But I can prompt you with a demonſtration wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Inuectiues haue been too bold. Do you remember what you writ in your Item for Earthquakes, <hi>of douhle fac'd</hi> Iani, <hi>changeable Cameleons, Aſpen leaues painted ſheathes, and ſepulchers, Aſſes in Lions skinnes, dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill cockes ſlipperie eeles, dormiſe, &amp;c.</hi> Beſides your te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimoniall of Doctour <hi>Perne,</hi> wherein it pleaſed you of your ſingular liberalitie and bountie to beſtowe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this beautifull <hi>Encomium: A buſie and dizzie head, a brazen fore head, a leaden braine, a wodden witte, a copper face, a ſtonie brest, a factious and eluiſh heart, a founder of nouelties, a confounder of his owne and his friendes good giftes, a morning booke-worme, an after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone malt-worme, a right Iugler, as full of his ſleightes, wiles fetches caſts of legerdemaine, toyes to mocke Apes wiehall, odde ſhifts and knauiſh practiſes as his skinne can holde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all this, <hi>you defie cut and long taile, that can accuſe you of any ſcandalous part either in word or deede.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tully, Horace, Archilochus, Ariſtophanes, Lucian, Iulian, Aretine,</hi> goe for no paiment with you, their declamatory ſtiles brought to the grand teſt of your iudgement, are found counterfeit, <hi>they are a venemous and viperous brood of railers,</hi> becauſe they haue broght in a new kind of a quicke fight, which your decrepite ſlow-mouing capacitie cannot fadge with.</p>
            <p>Tuſh, tuſh, you take the graue peake vppon you
<pb facs="tcp:3264:17"/>
too much, who would think you could ſo eaſily ſhake off your olde friendes? Did not you in the fortie one Page line 2. of your Epiſtles to <hi>Collin Clout</hi> vſe this ſpeech?</p>
            <p>Extra iocum, <hi>I like your</hi> Dreames <hi>paſsing well: and the rather becauſe they ſauor of that ſingular extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary vaine and inuention which I euer fancied most, and in a manner admired onely in</hi> Lucian, Petrarch, Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, Paſquil.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dic ſodes</hi> (godamercie on <hi>Dicke Sothis</hi> ſoule, for he was a better dauncer than thou art an enditer, &amp; with his legges he made ſome Muſicke, there is none in thy letters) anſwere mee briefly I ſay to the point, haue I varied one vowell from thy originall text in this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legation. If not, I cannot ſee how the Doctours may well bee reconcild, one while to commend a man <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his writings ſauour of that ſingular extraordinarie vaine, which he onely admired in</hi> Lucian, Petrarch, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retine, Paſquil: and then in another booke afterward to come and call thoſe <hi>ſingular extraordinarie admired men, a venemous and viperous breed of railers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The auncienter ſort of Poets and Oratours ſhall plead their owne worthineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tullie</hi> neuer ouerreached himſelf in railing ſo much as in flatterie. His <hi>Phillippicks</hi> (ſound Phyſick applide to a body that could not diſgeſt it) are the things that eſpecially commended him to this art-thriuing age of ours, and had not theſe beene, hee would certainely haue beene ſentenced by a generall verdit of hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, for a timerous time-pleaſer.</p>
            <p>VVho cannot draw a curtaine before a deformed picture. <hi>Plautus</hi> perſonated no Paraſite, but he made him a ſlaue or a bondman.</p>
            <p>Fawning and croutching are the naturall geſtures
<pb facs="tcp:3264:17"/>
of feare, and if it bee a vertue for a vaſſaile to licke a mans ſhooes with his tongue, ſure it is but borrowed from the dogges, and ſo is biting too, if it bee accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with ouer lowd barking, or in ſuch wiſe as it cannot pinch but it muſt breake the fleſh and drawe bloud.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Horace, Perſeus, Iuuenall,</hi> my poore iudgment len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth you plentifull allowance of applauſe: yet had you with the <hi>Phrigian</hi> melodie, that ſtirreth men vp to battaile and furie, mixt the <hi>Dorian</hi> tune, that fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth mirth and pleaſure, your vnſugred pilles (howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer excellently medicinable) would not haue beene ſo harſh in the ſwallowing. So likewiſe <hi>Archilochus,</hi> thou like the preachers to the Curtizans in Roome, that expound to them all Lawe and no Goſpell, art all gall and no ſpleene. Hence came it to paſſe, that with the meere efficacy of thy incenſed <hi>Iambicks</hi> thou madſt a man runne and hang himſelfe that had an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerd thee.</p>
            <p>Thee I imbrace <hi>Ariſtophanes,</hi> not ſo much for thy Comeedie of the clowd which thou wrotſt againſt phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, as for in al other thy inuentions thou inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeſt delight with reprehenſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucian, Iulian, Aretine,</hi> all three admirably bleſt in the abundant giftes of art and nature: yet Religion which you ſought to ruinate, hath ruinated your good names, and the oppoſing of your eyes againſt the bright ſunne, hath cauſd the worlde condemne your ſight in all other thinges. I proteſt were you ought elſe but abhominable Atheiſtes, I would obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defende you, onely becauſe <hi>Laureate Gabriell</hi> arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles againſt you.</p>
            <p>This I will iuſtifie againſt any <hi>Dromidote</hi> Ergoniſt whatſoeuer, there is no other vnlaſciuious vſe or end
<pb facs="tcp:3264:18"/>
of poetry, but to infamize vice, and magnifie vertue, and that if they aſſemble all the examples of verſe-founders from <hi>Homer</hi> to <hi>Hugh Copland,</hi> they ſhall not find anie of them but hath encountred with the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall abuſes of his times.</p>
            <p>Whatſoeuer harpeth not of one theſe two ſtrings of praiſe and reproofe, is as it were a <hi>Dirige</hi> in prick ſong without any dittie ſet to it, that haply may tickle the care, but neuer edifies.</p>
            <p>In the Romaine common-wealths it was lawful for Poets to reproue that enormitie in the higheſt chairs of authoritie, which none elſe durſt touch, alwaies the ſacred Maieſtie of their <hi>Auguſtus</hi> kept inuiolate: for that was a Plannet exalted aboue their Hexameter horizon, &amp; it was capitall to them in the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree to diſpute of his ſetting and riſing, or ſearch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitiuely into his predominance and influence.</p>
            <p>The ſecrets of God muſt not be ſearcht into. Kings are Gods on earth, their actions muſt not be ſounded by their ſubiects.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seneca Neroes</hi> Tutor, founde his death in no verſe but <hi>Octauia.</hi> Imperious <hi>Lucan</hi> ſprinkled but one drop of bloud on his imperiall chayre, and periſht by him alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ouid</hi> once ſaw <hi>Auguſtus</hi> in a place where he would not haue beene ſeene, he was exilde preſently to thoſe countries no happy man hears of.</p>
            <p>Long might hee in a blinde Metamorphoſis haue playd vppon all the wenches in Roome, and regiſtred their priuie ſcapes, vpbrayded inhoſpitalitie with the fable of <hi>Licaon</hi>: alluded to ſome Ambodexter Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer vnder the ſtorie of <hi>Battus</hi>: haue deſcribed a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnthrift, whoſe ſubſtaunce hawkes and houndes haue deuoured, in the tale of <hi>Acteon,</hi> that was eaten
<pb facs="tcp:3264:18"/>
vp by his owne dogges: mockt Alcumiſtes with <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi>: picturde inamaratos vnder <hi>Narciſſas</hi>: and ſhrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a picked effeminate Carpet Knight vnder the fictionate perſon of <hi>Hermophroditus</hi>; with a thouſand more ſuch vnexileable ouer-thwart merrimentes, if luſt had not led him beyond the proſpect of his birth, or hee ſeene a meaner man ſinning than an Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sancta Maria ora pro nobis,</hi> how hath my pen loſt it ſelfe in a croude of Poets.</p>
            <p>Gaffer <hi>Iobbernoule,</hi> once more well ouer-taken, how doſt thou, how doſt thou? holde vp thy heade man, take no care, though <hi>Greene</hi> be dead, yet I may liue to doe thee good.</p>
            <p>But <hi>by the meanes of his death thou art depriued of the remedie in lawe which thou intendedſt to haue had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him for calling thy Father Ropemaker</hi> Mas thats true, what Action will it beare? <hi>Nihil pro nihilo,</hi> none in law, what it will doe vpon the ſtage cannot tell; for there a man maye make action beſides his part, when he hath nothing at all to ſay: and if there, it is but a clowniſh action that it will beare: for what can bee made of a Ropemaker more than a Clowne. <hi>Will Kempe,</hi> I miſtruſt it will fall to thy lot for a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment one of theſe dayes.</p>
            <p>In ſhort tearmes thus I demur vpon thy long Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh-tayld declaration againſt <hi>Greene.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hee inherited more vertues than vices, a iolly long red peake like the ſpire of a ſteeple hee cheriſht con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually without cutting, where ta man might hang a Iewell, it was ſo ſharpe and pendant.</p>
            <p>VVhy ſhould art anſwer for the infirmities of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners? Hee had his faultes, and thou thy follyes.</p>
            <p>Debt and deadly ſinne who is not ſubiect to?
<pb facs="tcp:3264:19"/>
with any notorious crime I neuer knew him tainted; (&amp; yet tainting is no infamous ſurgerie for him that, hath beene in ſo many hote skirmiſhes).</p>
            <p>A good fellowe hee was, and would haue drunke with thee for more <hi>angels</hi> then the Lord thou libeldſt on, <hi>gaue thee in Christs Colledge,</hi> and in one yeare hee piſt as much againſt the walls, as thou and thy two brothers ſpent in three.</p>
            <p>In a night &amp; a day would he haue yarkt vp a Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet as well as in ſeauen yeare, and glad was that Printer that might bee ſo bleſt to pay him deare for the very dregs of his wit.</p>
            <p>Hee made no account of winning credite by his workes, as thou doſt, that doſt no good workes, but thinkes to bee famoſed by a ſtrong faith of thy owne worthines, his only care was to haue a ſpel in his purſe to coniure vp a good cuppe of wine with at all times.</p>
            <p>For the lowſie circumſtance of his pouerty before his death, and ſending that miſerable writte to his wife, it cannot be but thou lyeſt learned <hi>Gabriell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I and one of my fellowes <hi>Will. Monox</hi> (Haſt thou neuer heard of him and his great dagger?) were in company with him a month before he died, at that fatall banquet of Rheniſh wine and pickled hearing, (if thou wilt needs haue it ſo) and then the inuento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his apparrell came to more than three ſhillings (though thou ſaiſt the contrarie.) I know a Broker in a ſpruce leather ierkin with a great number of golde Rings on his fingers, and a bunch of keies at his gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, ſhall giue you thirty ſhillings for the doublet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, if you can helpe him to it. Harke in your eare, hee had a very faire Cloake with ſleeues, of a graue gooſe turd greene, it would ſerue you as fine as may bee: No more words if you bee wiſe play the good
<pb facs="tcp:3264:19"/>
husband and liſten after it, you may buy it ten ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings better cheape than it coſt him. By S. Siluer it is good to bee circumſpect in caſting for the worlde, theres a great many ropes go to ten ſhillings. If you want a greaſy paire of ſilk ſtockings alſo to ſhew your ſelfe in at the Court, they are there to be had too a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his moueables. <hi>Frustra fit per plura quod fieri potest per pauciora</hi>: It is policie to take a rich penni-worth whiles it is offred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alas euen his fellow writer that proper yoong man,</hi> almoſt ſcorns to cope with thee thou art ſuch a crow troden Aſſe: doſt thou <hi>in ſome reſpectes wiſh him well and ſpare his name?</hi> in ſome reſpects ſo doth hee wiſh thee as well? (<hi>hoc est,</hi> to be as well knowne for a foole as my Lord <hi>Welles</hi>) and promiſeth by me to talke ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſparingly of thy praiſe. For thy name, hee will not ſtoupe to plucke it out of the mire, and put it in his mouth.</p>
            <p>By this bleſſed cuppe of ſacke which I now holde in my hand, and drinke to the health of all Chriſten ſoules in, thou art a puiſſant Epitapher.</p>
            <p>Yea? thy Muſes foot of the twelues; old long Meg of Weſtminſter? Then I trowe thou wilt ſtride ouer <hi>Greenes</hi> graue and not ſtumble: If you doe, wee ſhall come to your taking vp.</p>
            <q>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Letter.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here lies the man whom Miſtris <hi>Iſam</hi> cround with bays,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>She, ſhe that ioyd to heare her Nightingales ſweete lays.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Comment.</speaker>
                  <l>Here Miſtris <hi>Iſam Gabriel</hi> floutes thy bays,</l>
                  <l>Scratch out his eyes that printeth thy diſpraiſe.</l>
               </sp>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>She, ſhe</hi> will ſcratch, and like a ſcritching night-owle come and make a diſmal noiſe vnder thy cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:3264:20"/>
windowe for deriding her ſo dunſtically. A bigge fat luſty wench it is, that hath an arme like an Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, and will bang thee abhominationly if euer ſhee catch thee in her quarters. It is not your <hi>Poet Gariſh, and your forehorſe of the pariſh</hi> that ſhall redeeme you from her fingers, but ſhee will <hi>make actuall proofe of you,</hi> according as you deſire of God in the vnder fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing lines.</p>
            <p>The next weeke Maiſter <hi>Bird</hi> (if his inke-pot haue a cleare current) hee will haue at you with a cap-caſe full of French occurrences, that is, ſhape you a meſſe of newes out of the ſecond courſe of his conceit, as his brother is ſaid out of the fabulous abundance of his braine to haue inuented the newes out of <hi>Calabria, (Iohn Doletas</hi> propheſie of flying dragons, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets, Earthquakes, and inundations.)</p>
            <p>I am ſure it is not yet worne out of mens ſcorn, for euery Miller made a comment of it, and not an oyſter wife but mockt it.</p>
            <p>When that fly-boat of Frenchery is once launcht, your trenchor attendant <hi>Gamaliel Hobgoblin</hi> intends to tickle vp a Treatiſe of the barly kurnell which you ſet in your garden, out of which there ſprung (as you auouched (twelue ſeuerall eares of corne at one time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Redoubted</hi> Parma <hi>was neuer ſo matcht</hi> if hee kindle the match of his meeterdome, and let driue at him with a volley of verſes. Let not his principalitie truſt too much to it, becauſe his name is Latin for a ſhield; for <hi>Poet Hobbinoll</hi> hauing <hi>a gallant wit and a brazen penne, will honourably bethinke him, and euen ambitiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly frame his ſtile to a noble emulation of</hi> Liuie, Homer, <hi>and the diuineſt ſpirites of all ages,</hi> as hee hath done to the emulation of <hi>Tullie</hi> heeretofore, when hee
<pb facs="tcp:3264:20"/>
compiled a Pamphlet, called <hi>Ciceranis Conſolatio ad Dolobellam,</hi> and publiſht it as a newe part of <hi>Tullie,</hi> which had bin hidde in a VVall a thouſand and odde yeares and was found out by him before it euer found beeing.</p>
            <p>The circumſtance was this; going downe the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at Cambridge one ſummer euening, and asking certaine queſtions of the Eccho at Barnewell wall (as the manner is paſſing by) holding her verie narrowly to the poynt, ſhe reuealed vnto him what a treaſure ſhee had hidden amongſt her ſtones; namely, this new part of <hi>Gabrielis Cicenonis conſolatio ad Dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellam</hi>: and though ſhe was verie loath to diſcloſe it, yet becauſe ſhee knewe not how ſoone God might call her; <hi>videlicet,</hi> how ſodainely ſhee might fall; to diſcharge her conſcience before her death, ſhee would deliuer it vp as freely vnto him as euer it was hers, come and digge for it hee ſhoulde haue it. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer more glad was ſhee in her life, that ſince ſhee muſt needes ſurrender it to the light, ſhe had chaunſt vppon ſuch a Cardinall Corrigidore of incongruitie, and <hi>Tullies</hi> nexte and immediate ſucceſſour vnder <hi>Carre,</hi> to whoſe carefull repoliſhing ſhe might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it.</p>
            <p>Keepe it quoth ſhe?</p>
            <p>No, if it were a booke of golde it is THINE, reade it, new print it, dedicate it <hi>from thy gallery at Trinitie Hall</hi> to whom thou wilt.</p>
            <p>VVhether hee vſde a ſpade or a mattocke for the vnburying of it I know not, but extant it is, and of a hundred I haue heard that it is his.</p>
            <p>O <hi>Gabriell,</hi> if thou haſt any manhood in thy ſtarcht peake, looke vpon me and weepe not.</p>
            <p>From this day forward ſhall a whole army of boies
<pb facs="tcp:3264:21"/>
come wondring about thee as thou goeſt in the ſtreet and cry <hi>kulleloo, kulleloo, with whup hoo,</hi> there goes the Ape of <hi>Tully</hi>: tih he he, ſteale <hi>Tully,</hi> ſteale <hi>Tully,</hi> away with the Aſſe in the Lions skinne.</p>
            <p>Nay but in ſadneſſe, is it not a ſinful thing for a Scholler &amp; a Chriſtian to turne <hi>Tully</hi>? a Turke would neuer doe it.</p>
            <p>Be counſaild in thy calamitie, write no more <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolatios ad Dolabellam,</hi> but <hi>Conſolatio ad Doctore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brielem</hi>; thy ſelfe comfort thy ſelfe, and learn to make a vertue of contempt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ad ruentem parietem ne inclina,</hi> is a Prouerbe which would haue preuented all this, if thou couldſt haue ſufferd thy ſelfe to haue beene directed by it: for firſt and formoſt hadſt not thou ſtept forrh to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-prop the ruinous wall of thy brothers reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I had neuer medled with thee; if thou hadſt not leand too much to an olde wall, when thou pluckſt <hi>Tullie</hi> out of a wall, the damnation of this Ieſt had bin yet vnbegotten.</p>
            <p>He that hath born ſaile in two tempeſts of ſhame, makes a ſport of ſhippe-wracke of good name euer after.</p>
            <p>The wall of the welfare of Fraunce that is ſtarted from her King, her true foundation, thy writinges (more wretched than France) would faine cleaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to if they could tell how, and <hi>count it a felicity to haue the oportunitie of ſo heroicall an argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God helpe <hi>Alexander</hi> if hee haue no other Poet to emblazon his atchieuements but <hi>Cherillus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>High reſolued Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and vertuous Sir <hi>Iohn Norris</hi> Englands champions, enuied tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties confidence, vnworthy are your aduentures Ili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ades to bee reported by ſuch a ragged reede, as the
<pb facs="tcp:3264:21"/>
iarring Pipe of this <hi>Batillus.</hi> The Portugals &amp; French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens feare will lend your Honors richer ornaments, than his low-flighted affection (fortunes ſummer fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lower) can frame them.</p>
            <p>The ſeale that I ſet to your vertues be ſilence; the argument of prayſe is vnauthorized in any mans mouth but olde age.</p>
            <p>VVhen the better parte of youthes feruence is boyld away, and that the ſhowres of many ſorrowes haue ſeaſond our greene heads with experience, with the wither-fac'd weather-beaten Mariner, that talks quaking and ſhudderingly of a ſtorme that hee hath newly toyld through, our wordes will bee written in our viſage</p>
            <p>Euen as the ſunne, ſo no ſcience ſhines in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleate glory till it be ready to decline.</p>
            <p>Theſe be the concluſions that gray hairs prune &amp; cut downe the proſperitie of yong yeares with as faſt as it aſpires, but let the ſeare Oake looke himſelfe in the glaſſe of truth, and he ſhal find that <hi>Methuſalems</hi> bleſſing is imbecillitie beſtowed on any creature but the Foxe, who neuer is a right Foxe till he be ripe for the dunghill.</p>
            <p>If my ſtile holde on this ſober Mules pace but a ſheete or two further, I ſhall haue a long beard lyke an Iriſh mantle droppe out of my mouth before I be aware.</p>
            <p>Marry God forfend, for at no hand can I endure to haue my cheeks muffled vp in furre like a Muſcoui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, or weare any of this VVelch freeze on my face.</p>
            <p>O it is a miſerable thing to dreſſe haire like towe twixt a mans teeth, when one cannot drinke but hee muſt thruſt a great ſpunge into the cup, &amp; ſo cleanſe his coole porridge as it were through a ſtrayner ere
<pb facs="tcp:3264:22"/>
it comes to his lippes.</p>
            <p>This ſecond Epiſtle I haue ſaid prettily well too, I thinke we were beſt begin THIRDLY VVHERE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>AS, for feare a volume ſteale vpon vs vnlookt for.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="letter">
            <head>The Arrainment and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the third Letter.</head>
            <opener>To euerie Reader fauourably or indifferently affected.</opener>
            <p>TEXT ſtand to the Barre. Peace there belowe. <hi>Albeit for theſe twelue or thirteene yeares no man hath beene more loath or more ſcrupulous than my ſelfe &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The body of mee hee begins like a proclamation: ſufficeth it wee knowe you your minde though you ſay no more.</p>
            <p>Is not this your drift? you would haue the worlde ſuppoſe you were vrgde to that which proceeded of your owne good nature: like ſome that will ſeeme to bee intreated to take a high place of preferment vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them, which priuilie before they haue prayde and payde for, and put all their ſtrength to clymbe vp to.</p>
            <p>You would foiſt in <hi>non cauſam pro cauſa,</hi> haue it thought your flight from your olde companions ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuritie and ſilence was onely with <hi>Aeneas</hi> to carry your Father on your backe through the fire of ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and by that ſhift with a falſe plea of patience vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly driuen from his kingdome, filch away the harts of the Queenes liege people.</p>
            <p>The backe of thoſe creple excuſes I haue broke
<pb facs="tcp:3264:22"/>
in the beginning of my booke, if you haue anie new infringement to deſtitute the inditement of forgerie that I bring againſt you, ſo it is.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="letter">
            <head>Heere enters Argumentum a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonio <hi>humano,</hi> like <hi>Tamberlaine</hi> drawne in a Chariot by foure Kings.</head>
            <p>I THAT IN MY YOVTH FLATTERD NOT MY SELFE VVITH THE EXCEEDING COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENDATION OF THE GREATEST SCHOL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LER IN THE VVORLD, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ille ego qui quondam gracili modulatus auena.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ah neighbourhood, neighbourhood, dead and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried art thou with Robinhood, a poore creature here is faine to commend himſelfe, for want of friendes to ſpeake for him.</p>
            <p>Not the leaſt, but the greateſt Schollers in the VVORLD, haue not only but exceedingly fedde him fat in his humor of <hi>Braggadochio Glorioſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yea</hi> Spencer <hi>him hath often</hi> Homer <hi>tearmd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And Mounſier</hi> Bodkin <hi>vowd as much as he:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet cares not <hi>Naſhe</hi> for him a halfe peny.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Lamentable, lamentable, that an indifferent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toward ciuill Lawyer, who hath read <hi>Plutarch De v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilitate capienda ab inimicis,</hi> &amp; can talke of <hi>Titius and Semprouius,</hi> ſhould be no more ſet by, but SET BY, thruſt aſide, while his betters carry the bredth of the ſtreet before them.</p>
            <p>Miſery will humble the haughtieſt heart in the world: <hi>Habemus reum confitente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> he confeſſeth himſelf a ſinner in vnſufficiency, yet for all that the aduerſitie
<pb facs="tcp:3264:23"/>
of vniuerſall obloquy hath laide a heauie hande on him, ſtill he retaineth (like conceald land) ſome part of his proud mind in a beggers purſe, ſcorneth to ſay <hi>Fortune my foe,</hi> or aske a good word for Gods ſake of anie man.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the plainneſſe of his puft vp nature, he will defie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie man that dare accuſe him</hi> of that he is.</p>
            <p>VVhy, why, <hi>infractiſsime</hi> PISTLEPRAGMOS, though <hi>you were yong in yeares, freſh in courage, greene in experience, and ouer-weaning in conceipt</hi> (we will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe nothing that you giue vs) when you priuately wrote the letters, <hi>that afterward</hi> (by no other but your ſelfe) <hi>were publiquely diuulged</hi>; yet when the bladder is burſt that held you vp ſwimming in ſelfe loue, you muſt not be diſcontented though you ſink.</p>
            <p>I haue <hi>toucht the vlcer of your Oratourſhip,</hi> in requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the nick-name of <hi>The Deuils Oratour.</hi> An Vlcer you may well chriſten it, as an vlcer is a ſwelling, for it was a ſwelling of ambition, no <hi>modest petition</hi> of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie merit of yours that did craue it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The olde Foxe Doctour Perne</hi> throughly diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red you for a yoong Foppe, or elſe halfe a word <hi>of our high Chauncelors commendation</hi> had ſtood with him inuiolable as an Act of Parlament.</p>
            <p>Great men in writing to thoſe they are acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with, haue priuie watch-words of denyal, euen in the higheſt degree of praiſing; they haue many fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, whoſe dutifull ſeruice muſt not bee diſgrac'd with a bitter repulſe in anie ſuite though vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>It may bee ſome of theſe long deſeruers of his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers labourd him for thee, hee like <hi>Argus</hi> hauing eyes that pierce into all eſtates, ſaw thee when thou wert vnſeene of thy ſelfe, and knowing thee to bee
<pb facs="tcp:3264:23"/>
vnworthy of any place of worth, would not diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance his men in ſo ſmal a matter, but writ for thee very vehemently outwardly, when the ſoule of his letter (into which thy ſhallowe braine could not deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend) included thy vtter miſlike.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yong bloud is hot, youth hastie, ingenuitie open, abuſe impatient, choller ſtomachous temptations buſie.</hi> In a word, the Gentleman was vext, and cutte his bridle for verie anger.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The tickling and ſtirring inuectiue vaine, the puffing and ſwelling Satiricall ſpirit</hi> came vpon him, as it came on <hi>Coppinger</hi> and <hi>Arthington,</hi> when they mounted into the peaſe-cart in Cheape-ſide and preacht: needes hee muſt caſt vp certayne crude humours of Engliſh Hexameter Verſes that lay vppon his ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke, a Noble-man ſtoode in his way as he was vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting, and from top to toe he all to berayd him with <hi>Tuſcaniſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Mappe of Cambridge lay not farre off when he was in the depth of his drudgery, ſome part of the excrements of his anger fell vpon it: poore Doctour <hi>Pernes</hi> picture ſtoode in a corner of that Mappe, and by the misdemeanour of his mouth it was cleane de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signior Immeritò</hi> (ſo called, becauſe <hi>he was and is his friend</hi> vndeſeruedly) was counterfeitly brought in to play a part in that his Enterlude of Epiſtles that was hiſt at, thinking his very name (as the name of <hi>Ned Allen</hi> on the common ſtage) was able to make an ill matter good.</p>
            <p>I durſt on my credit vndertake, <hi>Spencer</hi> was no way priuie to the committing of them to the print. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting I may well call it, for in my opinion <hi>G. H.</hi> ſhould not haue reapt ſo much diſcredite by beeing
<pb facs="tcp:3264:24"/>
committed to Newgate, as by committing that miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuing proſe to the Preſſe.</p>
            <p>I haue vſually ſeene vncircumciſed doltage haue the porch of his Pa<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im pilfries very hugely peſtred with praiſes. <hi>Hay gee</hi> (Gentlemen) comes in with his Plowmans whiſtle in prayſe of <hi>Peter Scurfe</hi> the penne-man, and <hi>Turlery ginkes</hi> in a light foote Iigge libels in commendation of little witte verie loftily: but for an Author to renounce his Chriſtendome to write in his owne commendation, to refuſe the name which his Godfathers and Godmothers gaue him in his baptiſme, and call himſelfe <hi>a welwiller to both the writers,</hi> when hee is the onely writer himſelfe; with what face doe you thinke hee can aunſwere it at the day of iudgement? <hi>Eſt in te facies ſunt apti luſibus anni, Gabriell,</hi> thou canſt play at faſt and looſe as well as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie man in England.</p>
            <p>I will not lye or backbite thee as thou haſt done mee, but are not theſe thy wordes <hi>to the curteous Buyer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shew mee or</hi> Immerito <hi>two Engliſh letters in print, in all pointes equall to theſe, both for the matter it ſelfe, and alſo for the manner of handling, and ſay wee neuer ſaw good Engliſh in our liues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>I eſteeme them for two of the rarest and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest treaties, as well for ingenuous deuiſing, as ſignificant vttering, &amp; cleanly conueying of his matter, that euer I read in this tongue, &amp; I hartily thank God for beſtowing vpon vs ſuch proper and able men with their penne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You muſt conceit hee was in his chamber-fellowe <hi>welwillers</hi> cloke when he ſpake this, the white-liuerd ſlaue was modeſt, and had not the hart to ſay ſo much in his owne perſon, but he muſt put on the vizard <hi>of an vndiſcreete friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:24"/>It is not worth the rehearſal, <hi>he ſcribled it in ieaſt for exerciſe of his ſpeech and ſtile, &amp;c. and it was the ſiniſter hap of thoſe vnfortunate letters</hi> to be derided &amp; ſcoft at throughout the whole realme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſharpest part of them were read ouer at Counſell Table,</hi> and he referd ouer to the Fleet to beare his old verſe-fellow <hi>noble M. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alanger</hi> company.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There was no remedie for it but melancholy patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A recantation he was glad to make <hi>by way of arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles or poſitions,</hi> which hee moderates with a milder name of an <hi>apologie,</hi> &amp; that recantation purchaſt his libertie. VVherefore in gratefull lieu of the benefit he receiu'd by it (<hi>although he hath hitherto</hi> vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſuppreſt</hi> it) <hi>yet he means to take occaſion by this extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary prouocation to publiſh it, with not ſo few as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſuch Academicall exerciſes, and ſundrie other poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike diſcourſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I deeme he will be as good as his word, for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yet it hath beene his wont, if he writ but a letter to any friend of his, in the way of thanks for the potte of butter, ga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon of bacon, or cheeſe that he ſent him, ſtraight to giue coppies of it abroad in the world, and propound it to yong gentlemen he came in company with, as a more neceſſary &amp; refined methode of fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Epiſtles than the Engliſh tongue hath hitherto been priuy to.</p>
            <p>Lord that men ſhoulde bee ſo malitiouſly bent <hi>to frame a matter of ſome thing, he takes a pleaſurable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to behaue himſelf ſo that he may be laught at,</hi> how would you prate and inſult if you knewe as much by him, as he knows by himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Naſhe</hi> do thy worſt, the three brothers bid a Fico for thee, diſcommend thou them neuer ſo much, they will palpably praiſe, and ſo conſequently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe
<pb facs="tcp:3264:25"/>
themſelues more in one booke they ſet foorth, than thou canſt diſparage them in tenne: yea, rather than faile, Maiſter <hi>Bird</hi> ſhall leaue coppying out let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of newes, and meeter it miſchieuouſly in mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of their ſcurnlitiſhip and ruditie.</p>
            <p>Three to one <hi>parma foy</hi> is oddes, not one of them writes an Almanacke, but hee reckons vp all his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>Bee it ſpoken heere in priuate; <hi>Muſa Richardetti fatrizat ſat bene pretty:</hi> The Muſe of dappert Dickie doth ſing as ſweet as a cricket.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nostimanum &amp; ſtilum Gabriel</hi> it is thine own verſe in <hi>Aedes <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aldinenſes,</hi> all ſaue the inſerting of <hi>pretty</hi> in ſtead of <hi>certè</hi> for rimes ſake.</p>
            <p>Had Phiſition <hi>Iohn</hi> liu'd, or not dyde a little afore Dog-dayes, a ſinode of Piſpots would haue conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe</hi> ſhould be confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out repriue.</p>
            <p>The Spanyards cald their inuaſiue fleete agaynſt England the Nauie inuincible, yet it was ouercome. Lowe ſhrubbes haue outliu'd high Cedars, one true man is ſtronger than two theeues, <hi>Gabriell</hi> &amp; <hi>Richard</hi> I proclaime open warres with you: March on, <hi>Iocus, Ludus, Lepos,</hi> my valiaunt men at armes, and forrage the frontiers of his <hi>Fantasticallitie,</hi> as you haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tubalcan</hi> aliâs <hi>Tuball,</hi> firſt founder of Farriers Hall, heere is a great complaint made, that <hi>vtriúſque A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cademiae Robertus Greene</hi> hath mockt thee, becauſe hee ſaide, that as thou wert the firſt inuenter of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, ſo <hi>Gabriell Howliglaſſe</hi> was the firſt inuenter of Engliſh Hexameter verſes. <hi>Quid reſpondes?</hi> canſt thou brooke it yea or no? Is it any treaſon to thy well tuned hammers to ſay they begat ſo renowmed a childe as
<pb facs="tcp:3264:25"/>
Muſicke? Neither thy hammers nor thou I know if they were put to their booke oaths will euer ſay it.</p>
            <p>The Hexamiter verſe I graunt to be a Gentleman of an auncient houſe (ſo is many an engliſh begger) yet this Clyme of ours hee cannot thriue in; our ſpeech is too craggy for him to ſet his plough in, hee goes twitching and hopping in our language like a man running vpon quagmiers vp the hill in one Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable and down the dale in another, retaining no part of that ſtately ſmooth gate, which he vaunts himſelfe with amongſt the Greeks and Latins.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Homer, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil, two valorous Authors,</hi> yet were they neuer knighted, they wrote in Hexameter ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: <hi>Ergo, Chaucer,</hi> and <hi>Spencer</hi> the <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil</hi> of England, were farre ouerſeene that they wrote not all their Poems in Hexamiter verſes alſo.</p>
            <p>In many Countries veluet and Satten is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner weare than cloth amongſt vs, <hi>Ergo</hi> wee muſt leaue wearing of cloth, and goe euerie one in veluet and ſatten, becauſe other Countries vſe ſo.</p>
            <p>The Text will not beare it good <hi>Gilgilis Hebberde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our engliſh tongue is nothing too good,</hi> but too bad <hi>to imitate the Greeke and Latine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Stannyhurst</hi> (though otherwiſe learned) trod a foule lumbring boyſtrous wallowing meaſures in his tranſlation of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgil.</hi> He had neuer been praiſd by <hi>Gabriel</hi> for his labour, if therein hee had not bin ſo famouſly abſurd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Greene</hi> for diſpraiſing his practiſe in that kinde, <hi>Is the Greene Maiſter of the blacke Art, the Founder of vglie oathes the father of miſbegotten Infortunatus, the Scriuener of Croſſebiters, the Patriark of Shifters, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Monarch of Croſſebiters, the wretched fellowe
<pb facs="tcp:3264:26"/>
Prince of Beggars, Emperour of Shifters,</hi> hee had cald him before, but like a drunke man that remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers not in the morning what he ſpeakes ouernight, ſtill he fetcheth Metaphors from Conny-catchers, &amp; doth nothing but torment vs with tautologies.</p>
            <p>Why thou arrant butter whore, thou cotqueane, &amp; ſcrattop of ſcoldes, wilt thou neuer leaue afflicting a dead Carcaſſe, continually read the rethorick lecture of Ramme-Allie? a wiſpe, a wiſpe, a wiſpe, rippe, rippe you kitchin ſtuffe wrangler.</p>
            <p>VVert thou put in the Fleete for pamphleting? Bedlem were a meeter place for thee. Be not aſhamd of your promotion, they did you honor that ſaid you were Fleete-bound, for men of honor haue ſailde in that Fleete.</p>
            <p>VVaſt paper made thee betake thy ſelfe to <hi>Limbo Patrum,</hi> had it beene a booke that had beene vendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet, the opproby had beene the leſſe, but for Chandlers merchandize to be ſo maſſacred; for ſheets that ſerue for nothing but to wrappe the excrements of huſwiuerie in, <hi>Proh Deum,</hi> what a ſpite is it. I haue ſeene your name cutte with a knife in a wall of the Fleete I: when I went to viſit a friend of mine there. Let Maiſter <hi>Butler</hi> of Cambridge his teſtimoniall end this controuerſie, who at that time that thy ioyes were in the Fleeting, and thou crying for the Lords ſake out at an iron windowe, in a lane not farre from Ludgate hill, queſtiond ſome of his companions ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie inquiſitiuelie that were newlie come from Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, what nouelties they brought home with them, amongſt the reſt he broke into this Hexamiter inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatory very abruptlie.</p>
            <q>
               <l>But ah what newes doe you heare of that good Gabriel huffe ſnuffe,</l>
               <l>Knowne to the world for a foole, and clapt in the Fleete for a Rimer.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:26"/>Iſt true <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> haue I found you, It was not without foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that you burſt into that magnifical inſultation, I THAT IN MY YOVTH FLATTERD NOT MY SELFE, &amp;c. for M. <hi>Butler</hi> for a Phiſition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none of the leaſt Schollers, hath commended you exceedingly for a foole &amp; a Rimer. <hi>He that threatned to coniure vp</hi> Martins <hi>wit,</hi> hath written ſome thing too in your praiſe in Pap-hatchet, for all you accuſe him to haue courtlie incenſt the Earle of Oxford a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you. Marke him well, hee is but a little fellow, but hee hath one of the beſt wits in England. Should he take thee in hand againe (as he flieth from ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour concertation) I prophecie that there woulde more gentle Readers die of a merrie mortality ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by the eternal ieſts he would maule theee with, than there haue done of this laſt infection. I my ſelf that inioy but a mite of wit in compariſon of his tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in pure affection to my natiue country, make my ſtile carry a preſſe ſaile, am fain to cut off half the ſtreame of thy ſport-breeding confuſion, for feare it ſhoulde cauſe a generall hicket throughout England. <hi>Greene</hi> I can ſpare thy reuenge no more roome in this book, thou haſt Phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> with thee, cope thou with him &amp; let me alone with the Ciuilian &amp; Deuine, whom if I liue I will ſo vnceſſantly haunt, that to auoid the hot chaſe of my fierie quill, they ſhalbe conſtraind to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſconſe themſelues in an olde Vrinall caſe that their brother left behind him. Yet ere I bid thee good night, receiue ſome notes as touching his phiſicallity deceaſed. <hi>He had his grace to be Doctor ere he died.</hi> As time may worke all things. <hi>In Norfolke where hee pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed he was reputed a proper toward man at a medecine for the toothake, &amp; one of the skilfulleſt Phiſitions</hi> in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting the heauens water <hi>that euer came there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:27"/>
               <hi>How well beloued of the chiefeſt Gentlemen (&amp; Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomen eſpecially) in that ſhire,</hi> it is incredible to bee ſpoken. <hi>Aſtra petit diſertus,</hi> hee is gone to heauen to write more Aſtrologicall diſcourſes, his brothers liue to inherite his olde gownes, and remember his nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſayings, amongſt the which this was one: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ale Galene,</hi> farewell mine owne deare <hi>Gabriell: Valete hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae artes,</hi> heart and good will, but neuer a ragge of money.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tunc tuares agitur paries cum proximus ardet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cloth-breeches houſe is burnt, and the flame goes a feaſting to <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe</hi> houſe next.</p>
            <p>Neuer til now, <hi>Gregory Habberdine,</hi> went thy foure letters vp Newgate, vp Holburne, vp Tiburne, to hanging.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, by that which hath been already laid open, I doe not doubt but you are vnwaueringly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, this indigeſted Chaos of Doctourſhip, and greedy pothunter after applauſe, is an apparant Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican and ſinner, a ſelfe-loue ſurfetted ſot, a broken-winded galdbacke Iade, that hath borne vp his head in his time, but now is quite foundred &amp; tired, a ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in nothing but the ſcum of ſchollerſhip, a ſtale ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker at <hi>Tullies Offices,</hi> the droane of droanes, and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter drumble-bee of non proficients. VVhat hath he wrote but hath had a wofull end? VVhen did he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute but hee duld all his auditorie? his Poetry more ſpiritleſſe than ſmal beere, his Oratory Arts baſtard, not able to make a man rauiſhingly weepe, that hath an Onion at his eye. In Latin like a louſe he hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie legges, many lockes fleec'd from <hi>Tullie</hi> to carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way and cloath a little body of matter, but yet hee moues but ſlowly, is apparaild verie poorely.</p>
            <p>In Engliſh, ice is not ſo cold, yet on the ice of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb facs="tcp:3264:27"/>
will he ſlide. No wiſe man pittie him that peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth ſo wilfully.</p>
            <p>Iudge the world, iudge the higheſt Courts of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale from the miſcarried worlds iudgement (Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge and Oxford) wherein I haue treſpaſſed in <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe,</hi> that hee ſhoulde talke <hi>of gnaſhing of teeth, yong</hi> Phaetons, <hi>yong</hi> Icari, <hi>yong</hi> Chorebi, <hi>young</hi> Babingtons.</p>
            <p>Neuer was I in earneſt til thus he twitted me with the compariſon of a traitour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Babington,</hi> high was thy birth, I a bondſlaue of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune in compariſon of thee, thy fall greater than <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etons,</hi> thy offence as heynous as <hi>Iudaſſes.</hi> May neuer more ſuch foule ſeeds of offence be ſowne in ſo faire a ſhape, may they be markt alwayes to miſchiefe that meane as thou didſt. The braunches of thy ſtocke remaines yet vnblaſted with anie diſobedience. God forbid that our forheades ſhould for euer bee blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with our forefathers miſdemeanors. Die ill deeds with your vngratious ill dooers, the liuing haue no portion with the dead, hell once paid his due, heauen gates are open to ſucceeding poſteritie.</p>
            <p>Prate of <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe and his paltrie</hi> as long as thou wilt, I will play at put-pinne with thee for all that thou art woorth, but of thy betters gette thee a better diſcourſing penne before thou deſcantes of.</p>
            <p>L. <hi>Greenes inwardeſt companion pinched with want, vexed with diſcredit, tormented with other mens felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ouer-whelmed with his owne miſerie, in a rauing and frantike moode, moſt deſperately exhibiteth a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to the Deuill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>C.</hi> Heerein thou thinkſt thou haſt won the ſpurs from all writers, but God and Dame Fiction knows
<pb facs="tcp:3264:28"/>
thou art farre wide of thy ayme; for neither was I <hi>Greenes</hi> companion any more than for a carowſe or two, nor pincht with any vngentleman-like want, when I inuented <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pauper non eſt cui rerum ſuppetit vſus</hi>: only the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented meditation of learning generally now a dayes little valued, and her profeſſors ſet at naught &amp; diſhartened, cauſed mee to handle that plaintife ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect more ſeriouſly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ext with diſcredit</hi> (Gabriel) I neuer was as thou haſt beene euer ſince <hi>Familiaritas peperit contemptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> thy familiar epiſtles brought thee in contempt.</p>
            <p>Though I haue beene pinched with want (as who is not at one time or another <hi>Pierce Penileſſe</hi>) yet my muſe neuer wept for want of maintenance as thine did in <hi>Muſarum lachrimae,</hi> that was miſerably ſlouted at in M. <hi>Winkfields</hi> Comoedie of <hi>Pedantius</hi> in Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Colledge.</p>
            <p>How am I tormented with other mens felicitie, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaying, I know a Cobler that was worth fiue hundred pound, an hoſtler that had built a good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Inne, &amp; might diſpend forty pound yearely by his land, a Carman that had whipt a thouſand pound out of his horſe taile; if I had likewiſe reckond vp a rope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker, that by tormenting of hempe, &amp; going back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward (which the Deuill would nere doe) had turnd as many Mill ſixpences ouer the thumbe, as kept three of his ſonnes at Cambridge a long time, &amp; that which is more, three proud ſonnes, that when they met the hangman (their Fathers beſt chapman) would ſcarſe put of their hats to him, why then thou ſhouldſt haue had ſome colour of quarell, thy accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might iuſtly haue enterd his title <hi>pro aris &amp; focis,</hi> whereas now it is friuolous and forceleſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:28"/>The ſharpeſt wits I perceiue haue none of the beſt memories, if they had, thou wouldſt nere haue toucht mee with tormenting my ſelfe with other mens feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie; for how didſt thou torment thy ſelfe with other mens felicitie, when in the 28. Page of thy firſt tomo of Epiſtles thou exclaimſt <hi>that in no age ſo little was ſo much made of, nothing aduaunſt to be ſomething, Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers made of Ciphars,</hi> that is by interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, all thoſe that were aduaunſt either in the Court or common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth at that time, had little to commend them, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in account worthy preferment, but were meere meacocks &amp; Ciphars in compariſon of thy excellent out-caſt ſelfe that liu'dſt at Cambridge vnmounted.</p>
            <p>Hang thee, hang thee, thou common cooſener of curteous readers, thou groſſe ſhifter for ſhitten tap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterly ieſts, haue I <hi>imitated</hi> Tarltons <hi>play of the ſeauen deadly ſinnes in my plot</hi> of <hi>Pierce Penileſſe?</hi> whom haſt thou not imitated then in the courſe of thy booke? thou haſt borrowed aboue twenty phraſes and epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thites from mee, which in ſober ſadneſſe thou makſt vſe of as thy owne, when thou wouldſt exhort more effectuall.</p>
            <p>Is it lawfull but for one preacher to preach of the ten commandements? hath none writ of the fiue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes but <hi>Ariſtotle?</hi> was ſinne ſo vtterly aboliſhed with <hi>Tarltons</hi> play of the ſeuen deadly ſins, that ther could be nothing ſaid <hi>ſupra</hi> of that argument?</p>
            <p>Canſt thou exemplifie vnto mee (thou impotent mo<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te-catching carper) one minnum of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar deuice of his play that I purloind? There be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie men of one name that are nothing a kindred. Is there any further diſtribution of ſins, not ſhadowed vnder theſe 7. large ſpreading branches of iniquity, on which a man may worke, and not tread on <hi>Tarletons</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:29"/>
heeles. If not, what blemiſh is it to <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe</hi> to begin where the Stage doth ende, to build vertue a Church on that foundation that the Deuill built his Chappell.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gabriell,</hi> if there bee anie witte or induſtrie in thee, now I will dare it to the vttermoſt: write of what thou wilt, in what language thou wilt, and I will confute it and anſwere it. Take truths part, and I wil proue truth to be no truth, marching out of thy du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g-voiding mouth.</p>
            <p>Diuinitie I except, which admits no dalliance: but in any other art or profeſſion, of which I am not yet free, and thou ſhalt challenge me to trie maiſtries in, Ile bind my ſelfe Prentiſe too; and ſtudie throughly, though it neuer ſtande mee in any other ſtead while I liue but to make one reply, only becauſe I wil haue the laſt word of thee.</p>
            <p>I would count it the greateſt puniſhment that <hi>In ſpeech</hi> could lay vpon mee, to be bound to ſtudie the Daniſh tongue, which is able to make any Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man haue the mumpes in his mouth, that ſhall but plunge through one full point of it, yet the Daniſh tongue, or any Turks, or hogs, or dogs tongue what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer would I learne rather than bee put downe by ſuch a ribauldry <hi>Don Diego</hi> as thou art.</p>
            <p>Heigh drawer, fil vs a freſh quart <hi>of new-found phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> ſince <hi>Gabriell</hi> ſaies we borrow all our eloquence from Tauerns: but let it be of the mighty <hi>Burdeaux</hi> grape, pure <hi>vino de monte</hi> I coniure thee, by the ſame token that the <hi>Deuils dauncing ſchoole in the bottome of a mans purſe that is emptie,</hi> hath beene a gray-beard Prouerbe two hundred yeares before <hi>Tarlton</hi> was borne: Ergo <hi>no gramercy</hi> Dicke Tarlton. But <hi>the ſumme of ſummes is this,</hi> I drinke to you M. <hi>Gabriell,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:29"/>
on that condition, that you ſhall not excruciate your braine to be conceited and haue no wit.</p>
            <p>Since we are here on our prating bench in a cloſe roome, and that there is none in company but you my approoued good friends <hi>foure Letters and certain Sonnets</hi> your Pages; I will rehearſe vnto you ſome part of the Methode of my demeanour in <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, inſomuch as the principall ſcope of it is a moſt liuelie anatomie of ſinne, the diuell is made ſpeciall ſuperuiſor of it, to him it is dedicated, as if a man ſhoulde compile a curious examined diſcouerie of whoredome, and dedicate it to the quarter Maiſters of Bridewell, becauſe they are beſt able to puniſh it.</p>
            <p>Wherfore as there is no fire without ſome ſmoke; no complaint without ſome precedent cauſe of ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeuance; I introduce in a diſcontented Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler vnder the perſon of <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe,</hi> tragicallie exclaiming vpon his partial-eid fortune, that kept an Almes boxe of compaſſion in ſtore for euery one but him-ſelfe. He tels how he toſt his imagination like a a dogge in a blanket, ſearcht euerie corner of the houſe of Charitie to ſee if he could light on any that would ſet a new nappe of an old threedbare Cloake: but like him that hauing a letter to deliuer to a Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Lorde, when hee came to his houſe to enquire for him found no bodie at home but an ape that ſate in the Porch and made mops and mows at him; ſo he deliuering his vnperuſde papers to Powles Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, the firſt that took them vp was the Ape <hi>Gabriel,</hi> who made mops and mows at them, beſlauering the outſide of them a little, but coulde not enter into the contents, which was an aſe beyonde his vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:30"/>VVith the firſt and ſecond leafe hee plaies verie pretilie, and in ordinarie termes of extenuating, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dits <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe for a Grammer Schoole wit</hi>; ſaies <hi>his Margine is as deepelie learnd as</hi> Fauſte praecor ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lida, that <hi>his Muſe ſobbeth and groneth verie piteouſlie, bids him not caſt himſelf headlong into the horrible gulph of deſperation,</hi> comes ouer him <hi>that hee is a creature of wonderfull hope as his own inſpired courage diuinely ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſteth, wils him to inchaunt ſome magnificent</hi> Mecenas <hi>to honour</hi> himſelfe in honouring him, with a hundred ſuch <hi>grace wanting</hi> Ironies cutte out againſt the woll, that woulde ieopard the beſt ioint of <hi>Poetica licentia</hi> to procure laughter, when there crinckled crabbed countenance (the verie reſemblance of a ſodden dogges face) hath ſworne it woulde neuer conſent therevnto.</p>
            <p>Not the moſt exquiſite thing that is, but the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel Table Aſſe Richard Clarke, may ſo Carterly deride.</p>
            <p>Euerie Milke-maide can gird, with Iſt true? How ſaie you lo? who would haue thought it? Good Beare bite not? A man is a man though hee hath but a hoſe on his head.</p>
            <p>No ſuch light paiment <hi>Gabriel</hi> haſt thou at my hands; I tell thee where, when, and how thou ſhewdſt thy ſelfe a Dunſinall.</p>
            <p>Onely externall defects thou caſts in my diſh, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing internall in thee, but I prooue that it is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther excrementall.</p>
            <p>A fewe Elegeicall verſes of mine thou pluckeſt in pieces moſt ruthfullie, and quotes them againſt mee as aduantageable, together with ſome diſmembred Margine notes, but all is inke caſt away, you recouer no coſts and charges. With one minutes ſtudie Ile de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroie more, than thou art able to build in ten daies.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:30"/>Squeiſe thy heart into thy inkehorne, and it ſhall but congeal into clodderd garbage of confutatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thy ſoule hath no effects of a ſoule, thou canſt not ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle it into a ſentence, &amp; make euerie line leape like a cup of neat wine new powred out, as an Orator muſt doe that lies aright in wait for mens affections.</p>
            <p>VVhome haſt thou wonne to hate mee by light crawling ouer my Text like a Cankerworme.</p>
            <p>Some ſuperficial ſlime of poiſon haſt thou driueld from thy pen in thy ſhallow footed ſliding through my <hi>Supplication,</hi> which one pen ful of repurified inke will exceſſiuelie waſh out. Shall I informe thee (that vnfruitfullie endeuorſt to informe authoritie againſt me) why I infixed thoſe Poeticall latine marge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t notes to ſome fewe pages in the beginning of <hi>Pierce Penni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe</hi>? I did it to explaine to ſuch expected ſpiefaults as thou art, that it was no vncouth abhorrencie from the cuſtome of former writers, for a man openly to bewaile his vndeſerued ill deſtenie.</p>
            <p>In the vncaſing of thy brother <hi>Richard,</hi> I calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Natiuitie of the <hi>Astrologicall Diſcourſe,</hi> I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parentlie ſuggeſted what a lewd piece of Prophecie it was, I regiſtred the infinite ſcorne that the whole Realme intertaind it with, the Adages that ran vpon it, <hi>Tarltons</hi> and <hi>Eldertons nigrum</hi> THETA ſet to it, yet wilt thou that art the ſonne and heire to ſhameleſſe impudence, the vnlineall vſurper of iudgement from all his true owners, the HOYDEN and pointing ſtock recreation of Trinitie hall, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>anitas vanitatis &amp; omnia vanitas,</hi> inueſt that in the higheſt throne of Art and Schollerſhip, which aſcrutinie of ſo manie millions of wel diſcerning condemnations hath concluded to be viler, than newes mungrie, &amp; that which is vileſt of all, no leſſe vile than thy Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:31"/>Moſt voices, moſt voices, moſt voices; who is on my ſide who? VVhether is the <hi>Astrologicall Diſcourſe</hi> a better booke than <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe?</hi> Gabriel hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telow ſaies it is, I am the Defendant, and denie it, and yet I doe not ouercull my owne workes: His aſſetri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he countermures thus.</p>
            <p>Pierce Pennileſſe <hi>is a man better acquainted with the Diuels of hell, than the Starres of Heauen</hi>: Ergo, <hi>the Astrologicall Diſcourſe is better than the notorious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abolicall diſcourſe of</hi> Pierce Pennileſſe.</p>
            <p>Once againe I denie his Argument to bee of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full age. <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe</hi> is a better Starmunger than a Diuelmunger, which needeth no other FOR to corroberate it but this, that my yea, at all times is as good as his nay.</p>
            <p>How is the <hi>Supplication</hi> a diabolicall Diſcourſe, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than as it intreats of the diuerſe natures and properties of Diuels and ſpirits; in that far fetcht ſenſe may the famous <hi>defenſatiue againſt ſuppoſed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies</hi>; and <hi>the Diſcouerie of Witchcraft</hi> be called notorious Diabolicall diſcourſes, as well as the <hi>Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> for they alſo intreate of the illuſions and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie operations of ſpirits: Likewiſe may I ſay that thoſe his foure Letters nowe on their triall are foure notorious lowſie Diſcourſes, becauſe they lyingly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe little elſe ſaue <hi>Greenes</hi> lowſie eſtate before his death.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Churchyard</hi> our old quarrel is renued when no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe can bee faſtned on mee, this Letter leapper vpbraideth mee with <hi>crying you mercie,</hi> I cannot tell, but I think you will haue a ſaying to him for it. Ther's no reaſon that ſuch a one as he ſhould preſume to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termeddle in your matters, it cannot be done with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny intent but to ſtirre mee vp to write againſt you a
<pb facs="tcp:3264:31"/>
freſh, which nothing vnder heau'n ſhall draw mee to doe. I loue you vnfainedly, and admire your aged Muſe, that may well be grand-mother to our grand-eloquenteſt Poets at this preſent.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Sanctum &amp; venerabile vetus omne Poema.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Shores wife</hi> is yong, though you be ſtept in yeares, in her ſhall you liue when you are dead.</p>
            <p>For that vnaduiſed indammagement I haue done you heretofore, Ile be your champion hence forward againſt any that dare write againſt you. Onely as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you would light vpon a good cuppe of old ſacke when you are moſt drie, pocket not vp this ſlie abuſe at a rakehell rampalions hands, one that when an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie is deepe buried in the graue of obliuion, ſhall ſeeke to digge it vp againe, recall that into mens me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories which was conſumed and forgotten.</p>
            <p>Whoreſon Ninihammer, that wilt aſſault a man &amp; haue no ſtronger weapons.</p>
            <p>The Italian ſaith, a man muſt not take knowledge of iniurie till he be able to reuenge it.</p>
            <p>Nay but in plaine good fellowſhip, art thou ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent &amp; vnconceiuing, that thou ſhouldſt ere hope to daſh mee quite out of requeſt by telling mee <hi>of the Counter, and my hoſteſſe Penia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I yeeld that I haue dealt vpon ſpare commodities of wine and capons in my daies, I haue ſung <hi>George Gaſcoignes</hi> Counter-tenor; what then? VVilt thou peremptorily define that it is a place where no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, or Gentleman of credit euer came?</p>
            <p>Heare what I ſay, a Gentleman is neuer through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entred into credit till he hath beene there; &amp; that Poet or nouice, be hee what he will, ought to ſuſpect his wit, and remaine halfe in a doubt that it is not au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticall, till it hath beene ſeene and allowd in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifts
<pb facs="tcp:3264:32"/>
conſiſtory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grande doloris ingenium.</hi> Let fooles dwell in no ſtronger houſes than their Fathers built them, but I proteſt I ſhould neuer haue writ paſſion well, or beene a peece of a Poet, if I had not arriu'd in thoſe quarters.</p>
            <p>Trace the gallanteſt youthes and braueſt reuellers about Towne in all the by-paths of their expence, &amp; you ſhall vnfallibly finde, that once in their life time they haue viſited that melancholy habitation.</p>
            <p>Come come, if you will goe to the ſound truth of it, there is no place of the earth like it to make a man wiſe.</p>
            <p>Cambridge and Oxford may ſtande vnder the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowe of it.</p>
            <p>I vow if I had a ſonne, I would ſooner ſend him to one of the Counters to learne lawe, than to the Innes of Court or Chauncery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My hoſteſſe Penia,</hi> thats a bugges word, I pry thee what Morrall haſt thou vnder it? I will depoſe if thou wilt that till now I neuer heard of anie ſuch Engliſh name.</p>
            <p>There is a certaine thing cald <hi>christian veritie,</hi> &amp; another hight <hi>common ſenſe,</hi> and a third cleapt <hi>humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,</hi> they are more requiſite and neceſſary for thee, than <hi>modeſtie or diſcretion for mee and my companions,</hi> of which would thou ſhouldſt vnderſtand, we are ſo well prouided, that we can lend thee and thy brother <hi>Richard</hi> a great deale, and yet keepe more than wee ſhall haue need of for our ſelues.</p>
            <p>VVilt thou be ſo hardy and iron-viſaged, to gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay that thy brother Vicars Batchlours hood was not turnd ouer his eares for abuſing of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> I know thou haſt more grace than ſo, thou doſt not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict
<pb facs="tcp:3264:32"/>
it flatly, but ſlubbers it ouer faintly, and comes to recapitulate not confute ſome of the phraſes I vſde in the vnhandſoming of his diuinitiſhip.</p>
            <p>I my ſelfe in the ſame order of diſgracing thou ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles them foorth will haue them vp againe, and ſee if thou or anie man can abſurdifie the worſt of them.</p>
            <p>I ſay, and will make it good, <hi>that in the Aſtrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call diſcourſe thy brother (as if hee had lately caſt the heau'ns water, or beene at the anatomizing of the ſkies intrailes in Surgeons hall) propheſieth of ſuch ſtrange wonders to enſue from the ſtarres diſtemperature, and the vnuſuall adulterie of plannets, as none but hee that is bawd to thoſe celeſtiall bodies could euer deſcry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This too I will ratifie for truthable &amp; legible En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, <hi>that his Aſtronomy broke his day with his credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and</hi> Saturne <hi>&amp;</hi> Iupiter <hi>prou'd honeſter men than all the world tooke them for.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the whole Uniuerſitie hiſt at him,</hi> Tarlton <hi>at the</hi> Theater <hi>made ieaſtes of him, and</hi> Elderton <hi>conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his ale crammed noſe to nothing, in beare-baiting him with whole bundels of Ballads.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this he barely repeates without any diſproue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or denudation at all, as if it were ſo lame in it ſelfe, that it would adnihilate it ſelfe with the onelie rehearſall of it.</p>
            <p>For the gentilitie of the <hi>Naſhes</hi> (though it might ſeeme a humor borrowed from thee to bragge of it) yet ſome of vs who neuer ſought into it til of late, can proue the extancy of our aunceſtors before there was euer a ropemaker in England. Wee can vaunt larger petigrees than patrimonies, yet of ſuch extrinſecall things common to tenne thouſand calues and oxen, would not I willingly vaunt, only it hath pleaſed M. Printer both in this booke and <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe,</hi> to
<pb facs="tcp:3264:33"/>
intaile a vaine title to my name, which I care not for, without my conſent or priuitie I here auouch.</p>
            <p>But on the gentilitie of <hi>T.N.</hi> his beard, the maiſter Butler of Pembroke hall, ſtil I will ſtand to the death; for it is the very prince Elector of peaks, a beard that I cannot bee perſwaded but was the Emperour <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſius</hi> his, ſurnamed the Tyrant, when hee playde the ſchoolemaiſter in Corinth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gabriell,</hi> thou haſt a prety polwigge ſparrows tayle peake, yet maiſt thou not compare with his: thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for all by thy owne confeſſion <hi>hee makes haires,</hi> had neuer the art to twilt vp ſuch a grim triangle of haire as that.</p>
            <p>Be not offended honeſt <hi>T. N.</hi> that I am thus bold with thee, for I affect thee for the names ſake as much as any one man can do another, and know thee to be a fine fellow, and fit to diſcharge a farre higher calling than that wherein thou liu'ſt.</p>
            <p>VVhat more ſtuffe lurketh behind in this letter to be diſtributed into ſhop-duſt?</p>
            <p>Pierce Pennileſſe <hi>is as childiſh and gariſh a booke as euer came in print; when he talks of the ſheepiſh diſcourſe of the Lambe of God and his enemies, he ſaies, <hi>it is mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous and abſurd, and not to bee ſufferd in a Chriſtian congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; that</hi>
               </hi> Richard <hi>hath ſcumd ouer the ſchool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and of the froth of their folly made a diſh of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie breweſſe which the Dogs would not eate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If he ſaide ſo (as hee did) and can proue it (as hee hath done) by Saint <hi>Lubecke</hi> then <hi>The Lambe of God</hi> is as childiſh and gariſh ſtuffe as euer came in print indeede.</p>
            <p>I but how doth <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe</hi> expiate the coin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quination of theſe obiections.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Richard,</hi> whom (<hi>becauſe he is his brother, he there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:3264:33"/>
cenſures more curious and rigorous,</hi> in calling him M. H. <hi>than hee would haue done otherwiſe) red the Philoſophie Lecture in Cambridge with good liking and ſingular commendation, when Aperſea was not ſo much as</hi> Idoneus auditor ciuilis ſcientiae, <hi>Ergo, the Lambe of God</hi> beares a better Fleece than hee giues out it doth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A perſe a is improoued nothing ſince, excepting his old</hi> Flores Poetarum, <hi>and</hi> Tarletons <hi>ſurmounting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorique, with a little euphuiſme and Greeneſſe inough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gabriel <hi>reports him to the fauourableſt opinion of thoſe that know A perſe a his Prefaces, rimes, and the very companie of his Tarltonizing wit his Supplication to the Diuel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Quiet your ſelues a litle my Maiſters, and you ſhal ſee mee diſpearſe all thoſe cloudes well inough. That <hi>Richard</hi> red the Philoſophie Lecture at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> I doe not withſtand, but how?</p>
            <p>Verie Lentenlie and ſcantlie, (farre bee it wee ſhuld ſlander him ſo much as his brother <hi>Richard</hi> hath done, to ſaie he read it with good liking and ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.) Credite mee, any that hath but a little refuſe <hi>Colloquium</hi> Latine, to interſeame a Lecture with, and can ſaie but <hi>Quapropter vos mei auditores</hi> may reade with equiualent commendation and liking.</p>
            <p>I remember him woondrous well. In the chiefe pompe of that his falſe praiſe, I both heard him and heard what was the vniuerſall ſlender valuation of him.</p>
            <p>There was eloquent <hi>Maister Knox,</hi> (a man whoſe loſſe all good learning can neuer ſufficiently deplore) twas he and one <hi>Maister Iones</hi> of Trinitie Colledge, that in my time with more ſpeciall approbation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſt in thoſe Readings.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:34"/>Since I haue heard of two rare yong men <hi>M. M<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riton</hi> and another, that in ſupplying that place of ſucceſſion haue ſurmounted all former mediocritie, and wonne themſelues an euerlaſting good name in the Vniuerſitie.</p>
            <p>Theſe thou ſhouldſt haue memoriz'd if any, but thou art giuen to ſpeake well of none but thy ſelfe and thy two brothers.</p>
            <p>Thrice fruitfull S. Iohns, how many hundred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecter Schollers than the three brothers haſt thou nurſt at thy paps, that yet haue not ſhakte off obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie?</p>
            <p>Mellifluous PLAYFERE one of the chief props of our aged, &amp; auntienteſt, &amp; abſoluteſt Vniuerſities preſent flouriſhing. VVhere doe thy ſupereminent gifts ſhine to themſelues, that the Court cannot bee acquainted with them.</p>
            <p>Few ſuch men ſpeake out of Fames higheſt Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, though out of her higheſt Pulpits ſpeake the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of all ſpeakers.</p>
            <p>Let me adde one word, and let it not bee thought derogatorie to anie, I cannot bethinke mee of two in England in all things comparable to him for his time. Seldome haue I beheld ſo pregnant a pleaſaunt wit coupled with a memorie of ſuch huge incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible receipt, deepe reading and delight better mixt than in his Sermons.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sed quorſum haec,</hi> how doe theſe digreſſions linke in with our <hi>Subiectum circa quod?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Flaunting <hi>Richard</hi> and his Philoſophie Lecture, was vnder our fingers euen now, howſoeuer wee haue loſt him. Hold the candle, and you ſhall ſee me caſt a figure for him extempore: Oh hoh, I haue founde him without any further ſeeking. Giue me your eares
<pb facs="tcp:3264:34"/>
               <hi>Io Paean,</hi> God ſaue them they are long ones.</p>
            <p>Now betweene you and me declare as if you were at ſhrift, whether you be not a ſuperlatiue blocke for al you readd the Philoſophie Lecture at Cambridge: Brieflie, brieflie, let mee not ſtand all daie about you.</p>
            <p>His conſcience accuſeth him, hee is ſtroke ſtarke dumbe, onely by ſignes he craues to bee admitted <hi>in forma pauperis</hi> that we ſhould let him paſſe for a pore fellow, and he will ſell his birthright in learning with <hi>Eſau</hi> for a meſſe of porrige.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cura leues loquuntur,</hi> he hath but a litle cure to look too. <hi>Maiores ſtupent,</hi> more liuing would make him ſtudie more.</p>
            <p>For this once wee diſpence with you becauſe you look ſo penitentlie on it, but let not me catch you ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling any more ſuch twiſe ſodden ſawduſt diuinitie as <hi>the Lambe of God and his enemies,</hi> for if I do, Ile make a dearth of paper in Pater-noſter-rowe (ſuch as was not this ſeauen yeare) onelie with writing againſt thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A perſe a</hi> can doe it, tempt not his clemencie too much. <hi>A perſe a?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Paſſion of God howe came I by that name; my godfather <hi>Gabriel</hi> gaue it mee, and I muſt not refuſe it. Nor if you were priuie whence it came would you hold it worthie to be refuſed, for before I had the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of it hee beſtow'd it on a Noble man, whoſe new faſhiond apparrell, and <hi>Tuſcaniſh geſtures, crin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ſidenecke, eies glancing, fiſnomie ſmerking,</hi> hauing deſcribed to the full, he concludes with this verſe, <hi>Euerie inch</hi> A perſe a <hi>his termes and braueries in print.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hold you your peace <hi>Naſhe: that was before you were Idoneus auditor ciuilis ſcientiae.</hi> It may bee ſo, for thou wert a Libeller before I was borne. Yet vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:3264:35"/>
correction bee it ſpoken, I haue come to the ſchooles and purg'd rheume many a time, when your brother was Philoſophie Lecturer, he wanted no <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploſus pedu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> to ſpend away his houre that I could help him with.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What ſince I am improued</hi> you partly haue prooued to your coſt, and may doe more at large if God ſend vs more leyſure.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Flores Poetarum,</hi> they are flowers that yet I neuer ſmelt too. Ile pawne my hand to a halfe penny I haue readd more good Poets thorough, than thou euer hardſt off.</p>
            <p>The floures of your <hi>Foure Letters</hi> it may be I haue ouerlookt more narrowlie, and done my beſt deuoire to aſſemble them together into patheticall poſie, which I will here preſent to Maiſter Orator <hi>Edge</hi> for a Newyeares gift, leauing them to his <hi>wordie</hi> diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be cenſured whether they be currant in inke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horniſme or no.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſcious mind: canicular tales: egregious an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> when as <hi>egregious</hi> is neuer vſed <hi>in engliſh but in the extreame ill part. Ingenuitie: Iouiall mind: va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larous Authors: inckehorne aduentures: inckehorne pads: putatiue opinions: putatiue artists: energeticall perſuaſions: Raſcallitie: materiallitie: artificiallitie, Fantaſticallitie: diuine Entelechy: loud Mentery: deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perfidy: addicted to Theory: the worlds great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiarie: ſirenized furies: ſoueraigntie immenſe: abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant Cauteles: cautelous and aduentrous: cordiall liquor: Catilinaries and Phillipicks: perfunctorie diſcourſes: Dauids ſweetnes olimpique: The Idee high and deepe Abiſſe of excellence: The only <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorne of the Muſes: the Aretiniſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mountaine of huge exaggerations: The gratious law of Amnesty: amicable termes: amicable
<pb facs="tcp:3264:35"/>
end: Effectuate: addoulce his melodie: Magy polime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chany: extenſiuely emploid: precious Traynment: No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellets: Notorietie negotiation: mechanician.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor are theſe all, for euerie third line hath ſome of this ouer-rackt abſoniſme. Nor do I altogether ſcum off all theſe as the newe ingendred ſome of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, but allowe ſome of them for a neede to fill vp a verſe; as <hi>Traynment,</hi> and one or two wordes more, which the libertie of proſe might well haue ſpar'd. In a verſe, when a worde of three ſillables cannot thruſt in but ſidelings, to ioynt him euen, we are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes faine to borrowe ſome leſſer quarry of elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution from the Latine, alwaies retaining this for a principle, that a leake of indeſinence as a leake in a ſhippe, muſt needly bee ſtopt, with what matter ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chaucers</hi> authoritie I am certaine ſhal be alleadgd againſt mee for a many of theſe balductums. Had <hi>Chaucer</hi> liu'd to this age, I am verily perſwaded hee would haue diſcarded the tone halfe of the harſher ſort of them,</p>
            <p>They were the Oouſe which ouerflowing barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme, withdrawne to her Scottiſh Northren chanell, had left behind her. Art like yong graſſe in the ſpring of <hi>Chaucers</hi> floriſhing, was glad to peepe vp through any ſlime of corruption, to be beholding to ſhe car'd not whome for apparaile, trauailing in thoſe colde countries. There is no reaſon that ſhee a baniſht Queene into this barraine ſoile, hauing monarchizd it ſo long amongſt the Greeks and Romanes, ſhould (although warres furie had humbled her to ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremitie) ſtill be conſtrained when ſhe hath recouerd her ſtate, to weare the robes of aduerſitie, iet it in her old rags, when ſhe is wedded to new proſperitie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3264:36"/>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tere moribus praeteritis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Caius Caeſar in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Gellius loquere verbis praſentibus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou art mine enemie <hi>Gabriell,</hi> and that which is more, a contemptible vnder-foote enemie, or elſe I would teach thy olde <hi>Trewantſhip</hi> the true vſe of words, as alſo how more inclinable verſe is than proſe to dance after the horrizonant pipe of inueterate an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie.</p>
            <p>It is no matter, ſince thou haſt brought godly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction out of loue with thee, vſe thy own deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, raigne ſole Emperour of inkehorniſme, I wiſh vnto thee all ſuperabundant increaſe of the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar gifts of abſurditie, and vaineglory: from this time forth for euer, euer, euer, euermore maiſt thou be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonized as the <hi>Nun parreille</hi> of impious epiſtlers, the ſhort ſhredder out of ſandy ſentences without lime, as <hi>Quintillian</hi> tearmed <hi>Seneca</hi> all lime, and no ſande; all matter, and no circumſtance; the factor for the Fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and night Vrchins, in ſupplanting and ſetting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the true children of the Engliſh, and ſuborning inkehorne changlings in their ſteade, the galimafrier of all ſtiles in one ſtandiſh, as imitating euerie one, &amp; hauing no ſeperate forme of writing of thy owne; and to conclude, the onely feather-driuer of phraſes, and putter of a good word to it when thou haſt once got it, that is betwixt this and the Alpes. So bee it worlde without ende. Chroniclers heare my praiers. Good Maiſter <hi>Stowe</hi> be not vnmindfull of him.</p>
            <p>Thats well remembred, now I talke of Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clers, I founde the Aſtrologicall diſcourſe the other night in the Chronicle. <hi>Gabriell</hi> will outface vs it is a worke of ſuch deepe arte &amp; iudgement, when it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely paſt vnder record for a cooſening prognoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. The wordes are theſe, though ſomewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breuiated;
<pb facs="tcp:3264:36"/>
for he makes a long circumlocution of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the yeare</hi> 1583. <hi>by meanes of an Aſtrologicall diſcourſe vppon the great and notable coniunction of</hi> Saturne <hi>and</hi> Iupiter, <hi>the common ſort of people were almoſt driu'n out of their wits, and knew not what to doe: but when no ſuch thing hapned, they fell to their former ſecuritie, and condemned the diſcourſer of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame madneſſe and follie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ipſiſsima ſunt Ariſtotelis verba,</hi> they are the verie words of <hi>Iohn Tell-troth</hi> in the 1357. folio of the laſt edition of the great Chronicle of England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mehercule quidem,</hi> if it be ſo taken vp, <hi>Pierce Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nileſſe</hi> may well caſt his cappe after it for euer ouerta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it. But ſome thing euen now <hi>Gabriell</hi> thou wert girding <hi>againſt my praefaces and rimes, and the timpanie of my Tarltonizing wit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVell theſe be your words, <hi>praefaces and rimes,</hi> let mee ſtudie a little <hi>praefaces and rimes. Minimè verò; ſi ais nego.</hi> I neuer printed rime in my life but thoſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the beginning of <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe,</hi> though you haue ſet foorth,
<q>
                  <l>The ſtories quaint of manie a doutie flie,</l>
                  <l>That read a lecture to the ventrous elfe.</l>
               </q>
And ſo forth as followeth in chambling rowe.</p>
            <p>Praefaces two, or a paire of Epiſtles I will receyue into the protection of my parentage, out of both which, ſucke out one <hi>ſolaeciſme</hi> or miſhapen Engliſh word if thou canſt for thy guts.</p>
            <p>VVherein haue I borrowed from <hi>Greene</hi> or <hi>Tarl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, that I ſhould thanke them for all I haue?</hi> Is my ſtile like <hi>Greenes,</hi> or my ieaſts like <hi>Tarltons?</hi> Do I talke of any counterfeit birds, or hearbs, or ſtones, or rake vp any new-found poetry from vnder the wals of <hi>Troy?</hi> If I do, trip mee with it; but I doe not, therefore Ile
<pb facs="tcp:3264:37"/>
be ſo ſaucy as trip you with the grandlie. Ware ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of whetſtones in the darke there my maiſters.</p>
            <p>This I will proudly boaſt (yet am I nothing a kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to the three brothers) that the vaine which I haue (be it a <hi>median</hi> vaine, or a madde man) is of my owne begetting, and cals no man father in England but my ſelfe, neyther <hi>Euphues,</hi> nor <hi>Tarlion,</hi> nor <hi>Greene.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not <hi>Tarlton</hi> nor <hi>Greene</hi> but haue beene contented to let my ſimple iudgement ouerrule them in ſome matters of wit. <hi>Euphues</hi> I readd when I was a little ape in Cambridge, and then I thought it was <hi>Ipſe ille,</hi> it may be excellent good ſtill for ought I know, for I lookt not on it this ten yeare: but to imitate it I ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre, otherwiſe than it imitates <hi>Plutarch, Ouid,</hi> and the choiſeſt Latine Authors.</p>
            <p>If you be aduiſde I tooke <hi>ſhorteſt vowels and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt mutes</hi> in the beginning of my booke as ſuſpitious of being acceſſarie to the making of a Sonnet wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Maiſter <hi>Christopher Birds</hi> name is ſet, there I ſaide that you mute forth many ſuch phraſes in the courſe of your booke which I would point at as I paſt by: Heere I am as good as my word, for I note that thou beeing afraide of beraying thy ſelfe with writing, <hi>wouldeſt faine bee a mute,</hi> when it is too late to repent. Againe, thou reuieſt on vs and ſaiſt, <hi>that mutes are courſed and vowels haunted.</hi> Thou art no mute, yet ſhalt thou be haunted and courſed to the full. I will neuer leaue thee as long as I am able to lift a pen.</p>
            <p>Whether I ſeeke to bee counted a terrible bulbeg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or no, Ile baite thee worſe than a bull ſo that the thou ſhalt deſire ſome body on thy knees to helpe thee with letters of commendation to <hi>Bull</hi> the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that he may diſpatch thee out of the way before
<pb facs="tcp:3264:37"/>
more affliction come vpon thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All the inuectiue and ſatericall ſpirits ſhall then bee thy familiars,</hi> as the furies in hell are the familiars of ſinfull ghoſts to follow them and torment them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſſion: thou ſhalt bee double girt with girds, and ſcoft at till thoſe that ſtand by do nothing but cough with laughing.</p>
            <p>Thou ſaieſt I profeſſe the art of railing, thou ſhalt not ſay ſo in vaine, for if there bee any art or depth in it, more than <hi>Aretine</hi> or <hi>Agrippa</hi> haue diſcouered or diu'd into, looke that I will found it and ſearch it to the vttermoſt, but ere I haue done with thee ile leaue thee the miſerableſt creature that the ſunne euer ſawe.</p>
            <p>There is no kind of peaceable pleaſure in poetrie, but I can drawe equally in the ſame yoke with the haughtieſt of thoſe foule-mouthd backbiters, that ſay I can do nothing but raile.</p>
            <p>I haue written in all ſorts of humors priuately I am perſwaded, more than any yoong man of my age in England.</p>
            <p>The weather is cold, and I am wearie with confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, the remainder of the colde contents of this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle be theſe.</p>
            <p>He enuiouſly indeuors ſince he cannot reuenge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to incenſe men of high calling againſt me, and wold inforce it into their opinions, that whatſoeuer is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe,</hi> concerning <hi>Peſants, Clownes &amp; hipocriticall hot-ſpurs, Midaſſes, Buckram Giants, &amp; the mightie Prince of darkeneſſe</hi> is meant of them, let him proue it, or bring the man to my face to whome I euer made any vnduetifull expoſition of it, I am to be my own interpreter in this firſt caſe. I ſay in <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe</hi> I haue ſet downe nothing but that which
<pb facs="tcp:3264:38"/>
I haue had my preſident for, in forraine writers, nor had I the leaſt alluſion to any man ſet aboue mee in in degree, but onely glanc'ſt at vice generallie.</p>
            <p>The tale of the Beare and the Foxe, how euer it may ſet fooles heads a worke a farre off, yet I had no concealed ende in it, but in the one, to deſcribe the right nature of a bloudthirſty tyrant, whoſe indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite appetite all the pleaſures in the earth haue no powre to bound in goodnes, but he muſt ſeeke a new felicitie in varietie of cruelty, and deſtroying all other mens proſperitie; for the other, to figure an hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite: Let it be <hi>Martin</hi> if you will, or ſome old dog that bites ſorer than hee, who ſecretlie goes and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth country Swaines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Makes them beleeue that that honny which their bees brought forth was poyſonous and corrupt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That they may buy honny cheaper than by being at ſuch charges in keeping of bees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it is not neceſſary they ſhould haue ſuch ſtately hiues or lie ſucking at ſuch precious honnicombs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this (which is nothing elſe but to ſwim with the ſtreame) be to tell tales as ſhrewdly as mother <hi>Hub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard,</hi> it ſhoulde ſeeme mother <hi>Hubbard</hi> is no great ſhrewe, howeuer thou treading on her heeles ſo oft, ſhee may bee tempted beyonde her ten commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>A litle before this the foreſaid fanaticall <hi>Phobetor, geremumble, tirleriwhiſco,</hi> or what you will, cald forth the biggeſt gunſhot of my thundring tearmes ſteept in <hi>Aqua fortis</hi> and gunpowder to come and trie them ſelues on his paper Target.</p>
            <p>But that it is no credite <hi>Galpogas</hi> to diſcharge a Cannon gainſt a lowſe, thou ſhouldſt not call in vaine, thou ſhouldſt heare Tom a Lincolne roare
<pb facs="tcp:3264:38"/>
with a witnes, woe worth the daie &amp; the yeare when thou heareſt him. I feare blaſt thee nowe but with the winde of my weapon. With the waſt of my words, I lay waſt all the feeble fortifications of thy wit. Shewe mee the Vniuerſities hand and ſeale that thou art a Doctour ſealed and deliuered in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a whole Commenſement, and Ile preſent thee with my whole artillerie ſtore of eloquence.</p>
            <p>A bots on thee for mee for a lumpiſh leaden heeld letter dawber, my ſtile with treading in thy clammie ſteps is growne as heauie gated, as if it were bound to an Aldermans pace, with the irons at Newgate cald the widows Almes.</p>
            <p>Ere I was chained to thee thus by the necke, I was as light as the Poet <hi>Accius,</hi> who was ſo lowe and ſo ſlender that hee was faine to put lead into his ſhooes for feare the winde ſhoulde blowe him into another Countrie.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that catch Leopards ſet cups of wine before them; thoſe that will winne liking and grace of the readers, muſt ſet before them continually that which ſhall cheare them, and reuiue them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gabriell,</hi> thou haſt not done ſo, thou canſt not doe ſo, therfore rhy works neither haue, nor can any way hinder mee, nor benefit the Printer.</p>
            <p>Euen in the packing vp of my booke a hot ague hath mee by the backe. Maugre ſickneſſe worſt, a leane arme put out of the bed ſhall grind and paſh e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery crum of thy booke into pin-duſt.</p>
            <p>The next peece of ſeruice thou doſt againſt <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe,</hi> is the naming <hi>of him wofull poueretto, and pleaſant ſuppoſing thou puldſt him by the ragged ſleeue</hi>: Then matcheſt thou thy ſelfe to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes,</hi> and him to <hi>Irus, Irrita ſunt hac omnia:</hi> it is a ſleeueleſſe ieaſt, I
<pb facs="tcp:3264:39"/>
haue beiliu'd thee already for it, it toucheth the body and not the minde. Beſides I was neuer altogether <hi>Peter Poueretto,</hi> vtterly throwne downe, deſperately ſeperated from all means of releeuing my ſelfe, ſince I knew how to ſeperate a knaue from an honeſt man, or throw my cloake ouer my noſe, when I ſalied by the Counters.</p>
            <p>The ragged cognizance on the ſleeue, I may ſay to thee, carried meate in the mouth when time was, doe not diſpraiſe it yet, for it hath many high partakers. <hi>Quae ſequuntur huiuſmodi ſunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou turmoilſt thy <hi>pia mater,</hi> to proue baſe births better than the ofspring of many diſcents, becauſe thou art a muſhrumpe ſprung vp in one night, a ſeely mouſe begotten on a moulehill, that wouldſt fayne pearch thy ſelfe on the mountaines, when thy legges are too ſhort to ouercome ſuch a long iourney of glorie.</p>
            <p>My margent note, <hi>Meritis expendite cauſam,</hi> thou wouldſt rather than any thing wreſt to an enditment of arrogance, &amp; ſo branch mee into thy tiptoe ſtocke. I cannot ſee how thou canſt compaſſe it: For though I bad them weigh the cauſe by deſerts, yet I did not aſſume too much to my owne deſerts, when I expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulated, why Coblers, Hoſtlers, and Carmen ſhould be worth ſo much, and ſo much, and I a ſcholler and a good-fellow a begger. How thou haſt arrogated to thy ſelfe more than <hi>Lucifer,</hi> or any <hi>Miles glorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> in the worlde would doe, I haue already noted at large in his due place and order. If thou beſtowſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny curteſie on mee, and I do not requite it, then call mee cut, and ſay I was brought vp at Hoggenorton where pigges play on the Organs.</p>
            <p>Wert thou well acquainted with me, thou ſhouldſt
<pb facs="tcp:3264:39"/>
perceiue that I am very franke where I take, &amp; ſend away none empty-handed that giue mee but halfe an ill worde.</p>
            <p>It is a good ſigne of grace in thee, that thou confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt <hi>thou hast offences enough of thy owne to aunſwere, though thou beest not chargd with thy Fathers.</hi> Once in thy life thou ſpeakſt true yet, I beleeue thee, and pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thee. God make thee a good man, for thou haſt beene a wilde youth hitherto.</p>
            <p>Thy Hexameter verſes, or thy hue and crie after <hi>a perſon as cleare as Chriſtall,</hi> I do not ſo deeply com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, for al <hi>Maiſter</hi> Spencer <hi>long ſince imbrast it with an ouer-louing ſonnet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVhy ſhould friends diſſemble one with another, they are very vgly and artleſſe. You will neuer leaue your olde trickes of drawing M. <hi>Spencer</hi> into euerie pybald thing you do. If euer he praiſd thee, it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had pickt a fine vaine foole out of thee, and he would keepe thee ſtill a foote by flattring thee, til ſuch time as he had brought thee into that extreame loue with thy ſelfe, that thou ſhouldſt run mad with the conceit, and ſo be ſcorned of all men.</p>
            <p>Yet yet <hi>Gabriell,</hi> are not we ſet <hi>non plus,</hi> thy <hi>roiſter doiſterdome</hi> hath not daſht vs out of countenance. If anie man <hi>vſe boiſtrous horſe play, or bee beholding to Carters Logique,</hi> it is thyſelfe; for with none but clow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and royniſh ieaſts doſt thou ruſh vppon vs, and keepſt ſuch <hi>a flurting and a flinging</hi> in euerie leafe, as if thou wert the onely reaſty iade in a country.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Skolding thou ſaieſt is the language of ſhrewes, railing the ſtile of rakehels</hi>; what concludſt thou from thence? Do I ſcold? do I raile?</p>
            <p>Scolding &amp; railing is loud miſcalling and reuiling one another without wit, ſpeaking euery thing a man
<pb facs="tcp:3264:40"/>
knows by his neighbour, though it bee neuer ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all humanitie and good manners, and would make the ſtanders by almoſt perbrake to heare it. Such is thy inuectiue againſt <hi>Greene,</hi> where thou talkſt of his low ſines, his ſurfeting, his beggerie, and the mother of <hi>Infortunatus</hi> infirmities. If I ſcold, if I raile, I do but <hi>cum ratione inſanire, Tully, Ouid,</hi> all the olde Poets, <hi>Agrippa, Aretine,</hi> and the reſt are all ſcolds and railers, and by thy concluſion flat ſhrewes and rakehels: for I doe no more than their examples do warrant mee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The intoxicate ſpirit of griſly</hi> Euridice, I can toſſe ouer as lightly to thee, as thou haſt puft it to mee. My hart is praeoccupated with better ſpirits, which haue left her no houſe-roome: thou haſt no ſpirite as it ſhould appeare by thy writing, intertaine her and the ſpirit of the buttery out of hand, or thou wilt be bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten hand ſmooth out of Bucklars bury.</p>
            <p>VVhen I parted with thy brother in <hi>Pierce Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, <hi>I left him to be tormented world without ende of our Poets and writers about London, for calling them piperly make-playes and makebates, not doubting but they would driue him to this iſſue, that he ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to goe to the chiefe beame of his benefice, and there beginning a lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table ſpeech with</hi> cur ſcripſi, cur perij, <hi>ende with</hi> Prauum praua decent, iuuat inconceſſa voluptas, <hi>&amp; ſo with a trice truſſe vp his life in the ſtring of his ſance-bell.</hi>
               </hi> Now heere thou thankſt God thou art not ſo vncharitably bent to put ſo much wit in a ſpeech, like a Parſon in Lancaſhire that kneeld down on his knees in a zealous paſſion, and very hartily thankt God he neuer knew what that vile Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Romiſh Popiſh Latine meant. Did I exhort inke and paper to pray that they might not bee troubled
<pb facs="tcp:3264:40"/>
with him any more? Inke and paper if they bee true Proteſtants will pray, that they may not be contami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated any more with ſuch abhomination of deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as the three brothers Apocripha pamphleting.</p>
            <p>After all this foule weather enſueth a calme di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latement of others too forward harmefulnes, and thy owne backward irefulneſſe; thats diſpatcht, the court hath found it otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Then thou goeſt about to bribe mee to giue ouer this quarrell, and ſaiſt if I will holde my peace, thou wilt beſtowe more complements of rare amplificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vpon mee, than euer thou beſtowdſt on Sir <hi>Philip Sidney,</hi> and gentle Maiſter <hi>Spencer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou flatterſt mee, and praiſeſt mee.</p>
            <p>To make mee a ſmall ſeeming amendes for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries thou haſt done mee, thou reckonſt mee vp <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the deare louers and profeſſed ſonnes of the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Edmund Spencer, Abraham France, Thomas Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Samuell Daniell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>With a hundred bleſsings and many praiers thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treatſt mee to loue thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Content thy ſelfe, I will not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou proteſts it was not my perſon thou miſlikt</hi> (I am afraide thou wilt make mee thy Ingle) <hi>but my fierce running at Parſon</hi> Richard, <hi>excuſeſt mee by my youth, &amp; promiſeſt to cancell thy impertinent Pamphlet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were good hanging thee now thou art in ſuch a good mind; yet for all this, a dogge will be a dogge, &amp; returne to his vomit doe what a man can, thou muſt haue one ſquibbe more at the Deuils Orator, &amp; his Dames Poet, or thy penne is not in cleane life. I will permit thee to ſay what thou wilt, <hi>to vnderlie</hi> (as thou deſir'ſt) <hi>the verdit of Fame hir ſelfe,</hi> ſo I may lie aboue thee, LIE aboue thee, tell greater lies than thou doſt
<pb facs="tcp:3264:41"/>
no man is able.</p>
            <p>Thus O heauenly Muſe I thanke thee for thou haſt giu'n mee the patience to trauel through the tedious wilderneſſe of this Gomorian Epiſtle. Not <hi>Hercules</hi> when he cleanſed the ſtables of <hi>Aegeas,</hi> vnder-tooke ſuch a ſtinking vnſauorie exploit. By thy aſſiſtaunce through a whole region of golden lanes haue I iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neied, &amp; now am ſafely arriu'd at <hi>not ſpeedily diſpatcht but hastily bungled vp as you ſee.</hi> Graunt that all ſuch ſlow diſpatchers &amp; haſtie bunglers, may haue along time of reproach to repent them in, and not come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to corrupt the aire, &amp; impoſtumate mens ears with their pan-pudding proſe any more. So bee it, ſay all Engliſh people after mee, that haue eares to heare or eies to reade.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Feci, feci, feci,</hi> had I my health, now I had leyſure to be merry, for I haue almoſt waſht my hands of the Doctour.</p>
            <p>His own regenerate verſes <hi>of the iolly Fly, &amp; Gibeline and Gwelph</hi> ſome peraduenture may expect that I ſhould anſwere. So I would if there were anie thing in them which I had not anſwerd before, but there is nothing; if there were, hauing driuen his ſword to his head, I reſpect not what he can do with his dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Onely I will looke vpon the laſt Sonnet of M. <hi>Spencers</hi> to the right worſhipfull Maiſter <hi>G.H.</hi> Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of the lawes: or it may ſo fall out that I will not looke vpon it too, becauſe (<hi>Gabriell</hi>) though I vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently ſuſpect it to bee of thy owne doing, it is popt foorth vnder M. <hi>Spencers</hi> name, and his name is able to ſanctifie any thing though falſely aſcribed to it.</p>
            <p>The fourth letter of our Orators to the ſame fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable or indifferent reader, was a letter which this many a long ſummers day I dare ieopard my may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denhead
<pb facs="tcp:3264:41"/>
had line hidden in his deske, for it is a ſhir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans hoſe that will ſerue any man as well as <hi>Green</hi> or mee.</p>
            <p>To make ſhort, in it as fortie times before, he brides it and ſimpers it out a crie, No forſooth God dild you hee would not that hee would: None ſo deſirous of quiet as hee good olde man, who with a pure intent of peace, firſt put fire to the flame that hath hedgde him in.</p>
            <p>He hath preuented Maiſter <hi>Bunnie</hi> of the ſecond part of his treatiſe of Pacification, for like ſome craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ring leader of rebellion, when hee hath ſtirred vp a dangerous commotion, and findes by the too late examination of his fore vnexamined defects in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that ſo ſweet a roote will hardlie effect correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondent fruits ſtrait in pollicie to get his pardon, hee ſtrikes ſaile to that tempeſt of ſedition, and is thrice as earneſt in preaching pacification, obedience, and ſubmiſſion: ſo <hi>Gabriel</hi> when he hath ſtird vp againſt me what tumults he can in Stationers Shops, and left the quiuer of his enuie not an arrow vndrawne out, hee finds by the audit of his ill conſumed defectes that he is not of force inough to hold out, wherefore in pollicie to auoid further arrearages of infamie hee tires the text of reconciliation out of breath, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth by the interceſſion of <hi>a cuppe of white wine and ſugar, to be made friends with his fellow writers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It cannot chooſe but he muſt of neceſſitie be a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſore fellow, that is ſo familiar with white wine &amp; ſugar, for white wine in a maner is good for nothing but to waſh ſores in, and ſmudge vp withered beauty with. Well for all hee would haue <hi>Pierce</hi> make no warres on him, he makes warres on <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe,</hi> he be beggereth him again in this epiſtle verie boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifullie
<pb facs="tcp:3264:42"/>
hee ſaies <hi>that Lordes muſt take heede how they Lord it in his preſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Aſſe is the onelie Author he alleadgeth. That Greene is an Aſſe in print, and he a calfe in print.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That they are both chiefetaines in licentiouſneſſe, and truth can ſaie the abhominable villanies of ſuch baſe ſhifting companions, good for nothing but to caſt away themſelues, ſpoile their adherents, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For my beggerie let that trauell the countries, I haue ſaide more for it than a richer man would haue done, but that I take vppon me to Lord it ouer great Lords thou art a moſt lewd tungd lurden to ſaie it.</p>
            <p>Muſt they take heede how they Lord it in my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, what muſt they doe then in thy preſenee,</p>
            <q>
               <l>That ſitting like a looker on</l>
               <l>Of this worlds ſtage, doſt note with critique pen,</l>
               <l>Thy ſharpe diſlikes of each condition:</l>
               <l>Ne fawneſt for the fauour of the great,</l>
               <l>Ne feareſt fooliſh reprehenſion,</l>
               <l>But freelie doſt of what thee liſt intreate,</l>
               <l>Like a great Lord of peereleſſe libertie,</l>
               <l>Lifting the good vp to high honors ſeate,</l>
               <l>And th'euill damning euermore to die,</l>
               <l>For life and death is in thy doomefull writing.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Whereas thou ſaiſt the Aſſe in a manner is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Author I alleadge, I muſt know how you define an Aſſe before I can tell how to anſwere you; for <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Agrippa</hi> maketh all the Philoſophers, Oratours, and Poets that euer were Aſſes: and if ſo you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that I alleadge no Author but the Aſſe; for all Authors are Aſſes, why I am for you; if otherwiſe, thou art worſe than a <hi>Cuman<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Aſſe to leape before thou lookſt, and condemne a man without cauſe.</p>
            <p>What Authors doſt thou alleadge in thy booke,
<pb facs="tcp:3264:42"/>
not two, but any Grammer Scholler might haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadgd?</p>
            <p>There is not three kernels of more than common learning in all thy <hi>Foure Letters.</hi> Common learning? not common ſenſe in ſome places.</p>
            <p>Of force I muſt graunt that <hi>Greene</hi> came oftner in print than men of iudgement allowed off, but neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe he was a daintie ſlaue to content the taile of a Tearme, and ſtuffe Seruing mens pockets.</p>
            <p>An Aſſe <hi>Gabriel</hi> it is harde thou ſhouldſt name him: for calling mee Calfe it breakes no ſquare, but if I bee a calfe it is in compariſon of ſuch an Oxe as thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The chiefetaines of licentiouſnes, and truth can ſay the abhominable villanies of ſuch baſe ſhifting compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, good for nothing, &amp;c.</hi> I am of the mind wee ſhall not diſgeſt this neither.</p>
            <p>Anſwere me <hi>ſuccinctè &amp; expeditè,</hi> what one period any way leaning to licentiouſnes, canſt thou produce in <hi>Pierce Pennileſſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I talke of a great matter when I tell thee of a peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od, for I know two ſeuerall periods or full pointes in this laſt epiſtle, at leaſt fortie lines long a piece.</p>
            <p>For the order of my life it is as ciuil as a ciuil orenge, I lurke in no corners but conuerſe in a houſe of credit as well gouerned as any Colledge, where there bee more rare quallified men, and ſelected good Schollers <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>han in any Noblemans houſe that I knowe in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ltand.</p>
            <p>If I had committed <hi>ſuch abhominable villanies, or were a baſe ſhifting companion,</hi> it ſtoode not with my Lords honour to keepe me, but if thou haſt ſaide it &amp; canſt not proue it, what ſlandrous diſhonor haſt thou done him, to giue it out that he keepes <hi>the committers
<pb facs="tcp:3264:43"/>
of abhominable villanies and baſe ſnifting companions,</hi> when they are farre honeſter than thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>If I were by thee I woulde plucke thee by the beard, and ſpit in thy face, but I would dare thee and vrge thee beyonde all excuſe to diſcloſe and prooue for thy heart bloud what villanie or baſe ſhifting by mee thou canſt, I defie all the worlde in that reſpect.</p>
            <p>Becauſe thou vſedſt at Cambridge to ſhift for thy Friday at night ſuppers, and coſen poore victuallers and pie-wiues of Doctours cheeſe and puddinges, thou thinkſt me one of the ſame religion too.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Greene</hi> was, let ſome other anſwere for him as much as I haue done, I had no tuition ouer him, he might haue writ another <hi>Galataeo</hi> of manners, for his manners euerie time I came in his companie, I ſaw no ſuch baſe ſhifting or abhominable villanie by him. Something there was which I have heard not ſeene, that hee had not that regarde to his credite in which had beene requiſite he ſhould.</p>
            <p>VVhat a <hi>Calimunco</hi> am I to plead for him, as though I were as neere him as his owne skinne. A thouſande there bee that haue more reaſon to ſpeake in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe than I, who ſince I firſt knew him about town haue beene two yeares together and not ſeene him.</p>
            <p>But Ile doe as much for any man, eſpecially for a deade man that cannot ſpeake for himſelfe. Let vs heare <hi>how we are good for nothing but to caſt awaie our ſelues, ſpoile our adherents, praie on our fauourers, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour our Patrons.</hi> Haue I euer tooke any likelie courſe of caſting away my ſelfe?</p>
            <p>VVhom canſt thou name that kept me company and reapt any diſcommoditie by mee, I can name di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers good Gentlemen <hi>that haue beene my adherents
<pb facs="tcp:3264:43"/>
and fauourers a long time.</hi> Let them report howe I haue ſpoilde them, or praid on them, or put them to one pennie detriment ſince I firſt conſorted with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>Haue an eie to the maine-chaunce, for no ſooner ſhall they vnderſtand what thou haſt ſaid by mee of them, but theyle goe neere to haue thee about the eares for this geare one after another.</p>
            <p>My Patrons or anie that bind me to them by the leaſt good turne, there is no man in England that is or ſhall (for my ſmall power) bee more thankefull vnto than I. Neuer was I vnthankefull vnto any, no not to thoſe of whome for deedes I receiued nothing but vnperformed deede promiſing words. It is an honor to be accuſde and not conuinſt.</p>
            <p>One of theſe months I ſhall challenge martirdome to my ſelfe, and writ large ſtories of the perſecution of tongues. Troth I am as like to perſecute as be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted. Let him take vp his Croſſe and bleſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that croſſeth mee, for I will croſſe ſhinnes with him though euerie ſentence of his were a thouſande tunnes of diſcourſes, as <hi>Gabriel</hi> ſaith euerie ſentence of his is a diſcourſe. Quods, quods giue mee my Text pen againe, for I haue a little more Text to launce.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecretaries of art and nature, if it were not for fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous contentions, might beſtead the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-welth with manie puiſſant engins.</hi> As for example, <hi>Bacons</hi> brazen noſe, <hi>Architas</hi> wodden doue, dancing bals, fire brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing gourdes, artificiall flies to hang in the aire by themſelues, an egſhell that ſhall run vp to the toppe of a ſpeare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Archimides</hi> made a heau'n of braſſe, but we haue nothing to do with olde braſſe and iron.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Appollonius Regimontanus</hi> did manie pretie iug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling tricks, but wee had rather drinke out of a glaſſe
<pb facs="tcp:3264:44"/>
than a Iugge, vſe a little brittle wit of our owne, than borrow any miracle mettall of Deuils.</p>
            <p>Amongſt all other ſtratagems and puiſſant engins what ſay you to <hi>Mates</hi> Pumpe in Cheapeſide, to pumpe ouer mutton and porridge into Fraunce: this colde weather our ſouldiors I can tell you haue need of it, and poore field miſe they haue almoſt got the colicke and ſtone with eating of prouant.</p>
            <p>Conſider of it well, for it is better than all <hi>Bacons, Architas, Archimedes, Appollonius or Regiomontanus</hi> deuices: for <hi>Gabriell</hi> that profeſſeth all theſe, with all their helpe cannot make the bias bowle at <hi>Saffron Walden</hi> run downe the hill, when it is throwne down with the hardeſt hand that may bee, but it will turne vp the hill againe in ſpite of a mans teeth, and that which is worſt, giue no reaſon for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Parrat and the Peacock haue leiſure to reuiue &amp; repoliſh their expired workes,</hi> you ſpeake like a friend, wele liſten to you when you haue repoliſhed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired your perfected degree. A Demy Doctor, what a ſhame is it?</p>
            <p>Becauſe your books do call for a litle more drinke and a fewe more clothes when they are gone to bed, that is, when they lie dead, you thinke ours ſhould do ſo too. No, no, we doe not vſe to clappe a coat ouer a ierkin, or thruſt any of the children of our braine into their mothers wombe againe, &amp; beget them a new after they are once borne. If it bee a horne booke at his firſt conception, let it be a horne booke ſtill, and turne not cat in the panne, conuert the Pater noſter to a Primer, when it hath begd it ſelfe out at the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowes vp and downe the cuntrey.</p>
            <p>Thou didſt thou knewſt not what in eeking this thy ſhort-waſted Pamphlet, iwis as thou ſaiſt of thy
<pb facs="tcp:3264:44"/>
ſelfe, <hi>Thou art an old trewant, fitter to plaie the dumbe dogge with ſome antients, than the hiſſing ſnake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVho be thoſe antient dumbe dogs? we ſhal haue you a Martiniſt when all comes to all, becauſe you cannot thriue with the Ciuill Law, and that you may marry her for any thing you are a kindred to her, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you wil compare <hi>Whitegift and Cartwright,</hi> white and blacke together, name the higheſt gouernours of the Church without giuing them anie reuerence or titles of honour, imbrace anie religion which will be euen with the profeſſion that fauors not you.</p>
            <p>There is no baile or maine priſe for it, but wee muſt haue you in the firſt peeping forth of the ſpring, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching out of a Pulpit in the woods: you haue put on wolues raiment already, ſeduced manie ſimple peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnder the habit of a ſheepe in <hi>Wolfes</hi> print. If you proteſt &amp; lie any more, it is not your ending here like a ſermon, that will make you bee reputed for a ſaint.</p>
            <p>Readers, a decaied ſtudent lately ſhipwrackt with <hi>Si vales bene eſt,</hi> hauing foure Lightors of Letters, cleane caſt away on the rocks called the Biſhop &amp; his Clarks, deſires you all to pray for him, and he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend you all to God in the next ſermon he pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth for his brother <hi>Richard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He hath a mind to pay euery man his owne, though hee hath ſuſtained great loſſe in fight, <hi>that which he cannot effect he beſeecheth the Lord to accompliſh, and euen to worke a miracle vpon the deafe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lord if it be thy will, let him be an Aſſe ſtill. Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, I haue no more to ſay to the Doctor, diſpoſe of the victorie as you pleaſe, ſhortly I will preſent you with ſome thing that ſhal be better than nothing, onely giue mee a gentle hire for my durtie day labor, and I am your bounden Orator for euer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sonnet">
            <pb facs="tcp:3264:45"/>
            <head>Sonnette.</head>
            <l>Were there no warres, poore men ſhould haue no peace,</l>
            <l>Vnceſſant warres with waſpes and droanes I crie:</l>
            <l>Hee that begins, oft knows not how to ceaſe,</l>
            <l>They haue begun, Ile follow till I die.</l>
            <l>Ile heare no truce, wrong gets no graue in mee,</l>
            <l>Abuſe pell mell encounter with abuſe:</l>
            <l>Write hee againe, Ile write eternally.</l>
            <l>Who feedes reuenge hath found an endleſſe Muſe.</l>
            <l>If death ere made his blacke dart of a pen,</l>
            <l>My penne his ſpeciall Baily ſhall becum:</l>
            <l>Somewhat Ile be reputed of mongſt men,</l>
            <l>By ſtriking of this duns or dead or dum.</l>
            <l>Awaite the world the Tragedy of wrath,</l>
            <l>What next I paint ſhall tread no common path;</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Aut nunquam tentes aut perfice.</hi> Tho. Naſhe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Obſeruations for the Readers of this booke.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Item whatſoeuer for the moſt part is here in this booke in change of letter, is our aduerſaries owne Text, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varied words, either in this his conuicted</hi> Foure Letters, <hi>or ſome other fuſtie treatiſe, ſet forth by him heretofore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou that I am wreſted and vtterly diuorced from my owne inuention, &amp; conſtrained ſtill ſtill, before I am warme in any one vaine, to ſtart away ſodainely, and follow him in his vanitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Finally, Printers haue many falſe <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iches which are thus to hee drawen vp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond page of C. for Baboune brother. reade Baboune his brother. in the 7. for all<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gorized &amp; Abdias. reade allegorized Abdias. in the 8. for ſet hand, reade ſet his hand. idem for hea<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>men, read headman. in the firſt of D. for Liuor poſt quieſcat, reade Liuor poſt <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ata quieſcat. in the 5. for plaiſt<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of Doctourſhip, reade plaiſtrie or d<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ing of Doctourſhip. in the 7. for inſolent inckehorne worme, reade inſolent incke worme, in the 2. of E. for Aſſe in preſent, read Aſſe in preſenti in the 3. for beſtow vpon, reade beſtow vpon him. in the 5. for effect, read efficacie. in the 4. of F. for vertuous 5yr Iohn Norris, read victo<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ious Syr Iohn Norris. in the 5. page of H. for I intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in a diſcontented Scholler, read I introduce a diſcontented Scholler. in the 8. for His aſſentrion, reade His aſſertion. in the 5. of I. for verie companie, reade verie timpanie. in the 5. page of K. for in this firſt caſe, reade firſt in this caſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3264:45"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
